<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Antichristian principle fully discovered in a brief and true account of all the hellish plots, bloody persecutions, horrid massacres, and most inhumane cruelties and tortures, exercised by the papists, on the persons of Protestant dissenters from the Church of Rome, for the cause of religion only, as well as abroad as here in England, Scotland, and Ireland, from the very beginning till this present year, 1678 ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25653</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38626</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17810022</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17810022</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106662</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25653)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106662)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1114:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Antichristian principle fully discovered in a brief and true account of all the hellish plots, bloody persecutions, horrid massacres, and most inhumane cruelties and tortures, exercised by the papists, on the persons of Protestant dissenters from the Church of Rome, for the cause of religion only, as well as abroad as here in England, Scotland, and Ireland, from the very beginning till this present year, 1678 ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40 [i.e. 44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Numbers 27-29 repeated in paging only.</note>
                  <note>Contains marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106662:1"/>
            <p>THE Antichriſtian Principle fully Diſcovered, In a Brief and true ACCOUNT OF All the Helliſh Plots, Bloody Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Horrid Maſſacres, and moſt Inhumane Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties and Tortures, exerciſed by the Papiſts, on the Perſons of Proteſtant Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the cauſe of Religion only; as well abroad as here in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> from the very beginning till this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent year, 1678.</p>
            <p>Faithfully Collected out of divers both Ancient and Modern Hiſtories, Records, and Writings, for the Information and undeceiving of the People.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 137.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>O Daughter of <hi>Babylon</hi> who art to be deſtroy'd, happy ſhall he be that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeth thee as thou haſt ſerved us.</p>
            </q>
            <p>With Allowance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106662:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106662:2"/>
            <p>THe Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> growing great and mighty, Rich and Proud, at once loſt its humility, and purity of Religion, and aſſumed pollitick, and tyrannick Principles, which cauſed her defiled hands, to lay aſide the ſword of the ſpirit, and to make uſe of that bloody one of Perſecution, and to run into bloody and murtherous Practiſes, helliſh plots, and contrivances, devilliſh Machinations, and horrid, and barbarous Maſſacres, There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can better demonſtrate this Antichriſtian ſpirit than to give you a ſhort ſpecimen of all her bloody Acts, to ſhew you her ſword reaking with the goar of the Innocent, and I think it ought to be more preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, than all the force of Arguments, and diſputations in the World; for let even thoſe of her own Religion be judge, whether ſo many horrid, and barbarous Perſecutions, Deaths, and Torments, inflicted on men and women, for the ſake of Religion only, (and which we ſhall here briefly enumerate) can be according to the ſpirit of Chriſt, or the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, and do not rather entitle thoſe, who command and execute ſuch inhumane Acts, as to take away the life of man, and with fire and ſword to lay waſt Countrys; to ſubvert King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and deſtroy States under the Notion and name of Religion, and holineſs; to be called Tyrants, bloody and wicked Perſecutors, and the principles by which they act, and ſeek to juſtifie ſuch horrid mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous, and bloody Perſecutions, to be Diabolical, and Antichriſtian. Let I ſay all the world judge, by all the bloody Tragedies which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath acted, and promoted; whether that murtherous Principle be of Chriſt, or Antichriſt, of God or the Devil; or which is more near to his holy doctrine, and commands, to love our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and to do good to thoſe that diſpightfully uſe us, or to burn, hang, draw, torment, and put to Death, all ſuch as will not be of our minds, and Religion.</p>
            <p>The firſt then that flung away the ſpiritual Keys,<note place="margin">The Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes.</hi>
               </note> and ſtoutly began to brandiſh the bloody ſword of Perſecution, was Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 3d, who with it began to hack and hew the poor <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> ſo called from <hi>Peter Waldo,</hi> or <hi>Valdo</hi> of <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> whom God had raiſed up, to oppoſe the many corruptions of the Romiſh Church, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of Images, Reliques, Oyle, Candles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Merits, auricular confeſſion, Supremacy of the Pope, adoration of Images, Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, falſe miracles, Purgatory, praying to Saints, prayers for the dead, Extream Unction, and the like: ſo early were theſe things queſtioned and preached againſt. The perſecution of this <hi>Valdo</hi> and his followers,
<pb facs="tcp:106662:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106662:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106662:4"/>(which were increaſed to a very great Number,) began in <hi>France</hi> in the year 1160. <hi>Valdo</hi> himſelf being forced to fly into <hi>Daupheny,</hi> many into <hi>Picardy,</hi> where they were called <hi>Picards,</hi> many into <hi>Flanders,</hi> and into <hi>Alſatia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years in <hi>Picardy. Planders. Germany.</hi>
               </note> and ſo they ſpread themſelves, for the ſafety of their lives into all places.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Picardy</hi> by the Command of King <hi>Phillip,</hi> three hundred Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens houſes were burnt, and ſeveral walled Towns deſtroyed, and in <hi>Flanders</hi> whether thoſe of that party fled, ſeveral were burnt for this cauſe of their Religion. Neither were they ſafe who fled into <hi>Germany,</hi> for at <hi>Mayance,</hi> the Biſhop there cauſed no leſs then thirty five Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes of that place, to be burnt in one fire, and eighteen in another. And at <hi>Strasburg</hi> at the ſame time, by the Biſhop there, eighty perſons were burnt together, for profeſſing the ſame Tenents. Many then that fled into <hi>England</hi> for ſhelter,<note place="margin">England.</note> were cruelly put to death at <hi>Oxford.</hi> At <hi>Collen</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> 1163. were four men and one woman burnt. And in <hi>Spain</hi> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rolamation 'twas made Treaſon, to relieve theſe people or to ſuffer them to live in that Country; but liberty was given to uſe them at will and pleaſure, and none to be called to account for it. But theſe people ſtill increaſing, cauſed the Pope to ſet on work the bloody Inquiſition, which with Racks, Fire, torments, and other cruelties, have ſent ſo many good and holy men, for their Conſcience ſake out of this World.<note place="margin">France.</note> 
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1201 at <hi>Paris,</hi> was burnt a Noble Knight called <hi>Enrandus,</hi> and this perſecution ſtill continuing, the people of the <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> of <hi>Loyſe</hi> flying from their barbarous perſecutors,<note place="margin">Daupheny.</note> into the caves of the Mountains were all ſmother'd in thoſe caves by their cruel Enemies, where were found afterwards, no leſs then four hundred Infants, ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled in their Cradles, which ſome Mothers had carried thither at their backs, and in their dead Mothers Arms. In <hi>Daupheny</hi> many were alſo burnt, and the raging fire of perſecution flamed thorow the whole Land.<note place="margin">Piedmont.</note> And alſo in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> where there was ſcarce a Town or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that many had not been put to death. And at <hi>Turin</hi> one of them had his Bowels torn out of his Belly, and put into a baſon before his face, and after that they Martyr'd him.</p>
            <p>Theſe Countrys being ſo hot with the fire of perſecution; many of theſe poor people fled into <hi>Calabria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calabria.</note> where they began to plant and to build Towns and Citys, as St. <hi>Xiſt La Garde,</hi> &amp;c. Where they continued till the year 1560. where they were grieviouſly perſecuted by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the 4th. forcing them to leave their Houſes, and Habitations, and to fly into the Woods for ſhelter of their lives, but being there purſued by the Order of the <hi>Viceroy</hi> of <hi>Naples,</hi> moſt of them were cruelly and barbarouſly put to death by the Soldiers, and when they could not kill with the Sword, kept them ſo beſeiged, that they dyed with Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. At which time they rackt one <hi>Charlin</hi> ſo horridly, that his guts came out at his belly: and another they tormented eight hours upon the Rack, to make him confeſs ſtrange lyes, invented againſt their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106662:4"/>which he would not. Some were ſtrip'd ſtark naked, and whipt, to death with Rods of Iron, ſome drawn through the ſtreets, and burnt with fire brands, others thrown down from an high Tower, and ſome ſlaſhed with ſharp knives. And in one place by the Order of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitor <hi>Panza,</hi> eighty had their Throats cut, as Butchers do ſheep, then cauſing them to be divided into four quarters, he made their Limbs to be ſet upon ſtakes, for the ſpace of thirty miles, a bloody ſpectacle. Sixty women were cruelly rackt, ſo that the cords peirced their Arms and Leggs to the bones, and then being caſt into priſon dyed, all but nine of the handſomeſt, who were taken away from thence, and never heard of more: And thus they continued their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, till they had quite rooted out and extirped, all profeſſing that Religion in <hi>Calabria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Waldenſes</hi> in <hi>Province,</hi> who had fled thither out of <hi>Piedmont,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Province.</note> 
               <hi>Daupheny</hi> and other places, encreaſing and being near <hi>Avignion,</hi> the Popes Seat, he ſoon raiſed againſt them an horrid perſecution, but the greateſt was in the year 1360. in the time of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12th. in which many ſuffer'd, and continued more or leſs rigorouſly, to the year 1540. in which was the cruel Maſſacre, by the means of the Popes Agents, at <hi>Merindol</hi> and <hi>Chabriers, Pepin,</hi> and other places. Where the Towns were fired, wholly deſtroyed, and all the Lands about laid waſte. The poor people were ſlain, the young Virgins raviſhed and barbarouſly uſed, Children pulled alive out of their Mothers Bellies, the breaſts of divers women cut off, and their ſucking Children left on the floor, to dye with Famine, or ſucking the gore, that ran from the wounds of their dead Mothers. At <hi>Cabriers</hi> there being but ſixty ſix weak men left in the Town the reſt being fled, they cauſed them to be brought all forth to a field, and there the bloody Papiſts cut them to peeces. And all the women they found in the Town, with their young Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren they lockt up together in a Barn, and ſo ſet it on fire and burnt them: and ſome that endeavoured to eſcape thorow the flames, they knockt on the head with their Halberts, and ript open the bellies of others that were with Childe, their Children falling under their feet: and others being bound back to back, were broach'd in ſport upon one Sword. So that in this place were ſlain, above a thouſand, Men, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Children, that could not lift up their hands to reſiſt! At <hi>Coſta</hi> another Town, they committed great ſlaughters, and where they uſed ſeveral Women and Malds, that fled into an Orchard for ſafety, with ſo much cruel and inhumane beaſtlineſs; that they dyed moſt thereof. This long and bloody perſecution of theſe <hi>Waldenſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Collected out of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners. <hi>Cades</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> laſted near five hundred years, in which time they ſpread their Tenents over <hi>Bohemia, Auſtria, Germany, Flanders, England, Poland, Italy, Spain, Dalmatia, Oroatia, Sclavonia, Greecia, Livonia, Sarmatia,</hi> and <hi>Bulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> in all which places they were perſecuted, and tormented more or leſs, according as the Pope and his Miniſters had power, and Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces over the Princes, of thoſe Countrys.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106662:5"/>
            <p>The perſecution alſo of thoſe called <hi>Albingenſes</hi> was very notorious,<note place="margin">The perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingenſes.</hi>
               </note> they were of the ſame principles, and Tenents as the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> and differ'd only in Country and Name, being Inhabitants of the Country of <hi>Albi,</hi> the chief of whom was <hi>Arnold,</hi> from whom they were called <hi>Arnoldiſts.</hi> Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third began with them, and his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors followed his ſteps, and Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, raiſed a War againſt them, calling it the <hi>Holy War,</hi> and gave out the ſame pardons, and Indulgences, for encouragement of thoſe who went againſt theſe people, as he did to thoſe that went into the Holy Land, againſt the <hi>Saracens,</hi> in which War he ſo thundered againſt <hi>Raimond,</hi> Earl of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe</hi> that he was forced to ſubmit, and for penance to be led publiquely, ſtript to his drawers with a cord about his neck, and ſo whipt by the Fryers, nine times about the grave of one <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>Hermite,</hi> kill'd in that War: And then wou'd have forced him againſt his Conſcience, to have fought againſt the <hi>Albingenſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Legat playing the part of a General,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Beziers.</note> beſieges and takes <hi>Beziers</hi> by ſtorm, ſeting the whole City in fire, and burnt it to aſhes, and ſlew all they could meet with without diſtinction, both Catholicks, as well as thoſe they termed Hereticks, for there were of both in the City. At which time they ſlew in this City 60000 perſons.</p>
            <p>Their next morſel was the Town of <hi>Carcaſſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Carcaſſon <hi>Town.</hi>
               </note> which the Holy Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, as they called themſelves, took alſo by ſtorm, burning, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſlaying all, as they had done before at <hi>Beziers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After that they ſet upon the City of <hi>Carcaſſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Carcaſſon <hi>City.</hi>
               </note> defended by the Earl of <hi>Beziers,</hi> and when they offered to Capitulate the Legat would grant no other conditions, but that the Earl and twelve more ſhould come forth, with their baggage, but all the reſt both men women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſhould come forth ſtark naked, without covering of either Shirt or Smock, and humble themſelves before him. But they diſdaining ſuch unworthy, and ignominious terms, ſtand it out till they had told the Earl forth of Town, under pretence of parly with the Legat, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given his Oath for his ſafe return, but having him, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard thereto, ſtormed the City, to the amazement of the poor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed Citizens, who looked for nothing leſs, but there being a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Vault under ground, which went to a Caſtle not far of, moſt of them convey'd themſelves away by it, leaving their City and all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to the fury and rage of the unholy Pilgrims.</p>
            <p>Then they ſurprized the Caſtle of <hi>Beron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beron.</note> where they pull'd out the Eyes of an hundred <hi>Albingenſes,</hi> and cut off their noſes, leaving only one with one Eye to guide the reſt to <hi>Cabaret.</hi> They took alſo the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Menerby,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Menerby.</note> defended by the Lord of <hi>Termes,</hi> whom they flung in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a filthy Priſon till he dyed, his wife, ſiſter, and daughter, who was a Maid, they burnt in one fire, becauſe they would not recant their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And after that they caſt into one fire for the ſame cauſe, 180 men and women at the ſame place, who dyed rejoycing.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106662:5"/>
            <p>At the taking of the Caſtle of <hi>Lavaur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lavaur.</note> by <hi>Simon Monford</hi> who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Legat, in his Generalſhip, all the Souldiers therein were put to the Sword; except 80. Gentlemen, whom that cruel Earl cauſed to be hanged, and the Lord <hi>Aimery</hi> on a Gibbet, higher then all the reſt: And the Lady his Siſter eaſt into a ditch, and there covered with ſtones. The reſt of the people who were about 400. perſons, were forced into a great fire, made purpoſely for them, and ſo burnt, except thoſe that for fear recanted their Religion, which were ſew.</p>
            <p>At this time one <hi>Reynard Lollard,</hi> by his preaching ſtirred up the Engliſh in <hi>Guienne,</hi> to aſſiſt the <hi>Albingenſes,</hi> this <hi>Lollard</hi> was a holy man and a Prophet, and afterwards was burnt at <hi>Collen</hi> by the Papiſts: thoſe in <hi>England</hi> of that Judgment, were from him afterwards called <hi>Lollards.</hi> Theſe men ſtill proceeding in their cruelty againſt the <hi>Albingenſes,</hi> take the Town of St. <hi>Anthonys,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonys.</note> where they cauſed thirty of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal men to be hanged in cold blood, after they had granted them their lives, and ſeveral other Towns, where they put all to the ſword without diſtinction of Age or Sex.</p>
            <p>In the year 1213. near <hi>Muret,</hi> a Town upon the <hi>Garronne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Muret.</note> there were ſlain in battle in the purſute, and afterwards, about two Millions of <hi>Albingenſes,</hi> with the King of <hi>Araagon,</hi> who then took their parts.</p>
            <p>In the year 1215. Fryer <hi>Conradus</hi> of <hi>Marpurg,</hi> the Popes inquiſitor, moſt horribly tortured all that made profeſſion of the Goſpel, or were but ſuſpected, marking them with red hot Irons, and then giving them to the ſecular power to be burnt, ſo that neither Noble, nor Ignoble, Clerks, Monks, Nuns, Burgeſſes, Citizens, and Country people eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped the ſlames, by the-means of this bloody Inquiſitor.</p>
            <p>The Town of <hi>Miromand</hi> being taken, by Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Miromand</note> he deſtroyed there of the <hi>Albingenſes</hi> for the ſame cauſe, to the number of five thouſand men women and children.</p>
            <p>In the year 1234. many of theſe <hi>Albingenſes</hi> being fled into <hi>Spain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spain.</note> the Pope cauſed a <hi>Croiſado</hi> to be preached againſt them, whereby a great Army of Pilgrims aſſembled together, were ſent by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> againſt the <hi>Albingenſes,</hi> whom they ſlew, with their Biſhops and Teachers, burnt their houſes, deſtroyed their Towns, and plunderd and carried away their goods. And about the ſame time, thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired into a fenny place, on the borders of <hi>Germany</hi> were alſo all ſlain. At the ſame time alſo, many of them were ſlain and burnt in <hi>Millain,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Italy,</hi> beyond the <hi>Alpes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the year 1242. there were burnt in <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> 200. of theſe <hi>Albin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tholouſe.</note> being taken in a certain Caſtle hard by, and the year following 220. more, in the ſame place.</p>
            <p>In the year 1281. a great perſecution was raiſed againſt them, in <hi>Albi</hi> by one <hi>Gourdon,</hi> ſo that they were almoſt all extirpated and root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, and forced to fly for ſafety of their lives, to all parts.<note place="margin">Albi.</note> At the ſame time by the Popes Order, many of the chief preachers of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106662:6"/>
               <hi>Albingenſes</hi> bones, were dug up and burnt, 20. and 30. years after they had been buried.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luthers</hi> Forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and <hi>Cades</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. The perſe cution of the <hi>Bohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians. Ex-Hiſt. Perſecutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The perſecution of the <hi>Bohemians</hi> begun betimes, even neer the year 977. by Pope <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> and afterwards by <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> continuing down to the times of <hi>Mathias</hi> of <hi>Frague,</hi> 1375. and to <hi>John Hus,</hi> and <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> who were both burnt, in defence of the Goſpel at <hi>Conſtance,</hi> notwithſtanding the publique faith of <hi>Germany</hi> given them for their ſecurity.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Cuttenburg</hi> where there are many deep Mines in the year 1420. they threw into one of them 1700. perſons, and into another 1038. and into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> third 1334. perſons.</p>
            <p>In the year 1421. at <hi>Litomeritia,</hi> twenty four of the chief Citizens, among whom was the Son-in-Law of the chief perſecutor, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of the City, were thruſt into a great Tower, and almoſt famiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to death, from whence being at laſt drawn, becauſe they would not abjure their Religion, they were condemned to be all drowned, in the River <hi>Albis,</hi> which was accordingly done, their hands and feet being bound, and ſo thrown into the midſt of the River, and if the ſtream brought any of them to the ſides of the bank, they were goared to death with Iron forks and Pikes. The daughter of the chief perſecutor, ſeeing ſhe could not move her Father, by her tears and prayers, to ſave the Life of her Husband, flung her ſelf after him into the River, and embracing his body, periſhed with him, and was found the next day with him faſt in her Armes, and were buried in one grave.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time at <hi>Prague</hi> 4. men, 4 boys, and a Miniſter were then burnt in one fire, becauſe they adminiſtred and received the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in both kindes. Many and indeed innumerable were the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and torments, and unheard of babarities executed both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely and privately on thoſe poor wretches, by thoſe bloody Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners.</p>
            <p>About the year 1523. <hi>Martin Luther</hi> began to ſhine as a great light in <hi>Germany,</hi> and his Doctrine to overſpread thoſe parts, even to <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> which cauſed more violent perſecutions, wherein multitudes of Saints loſt their Lives, by the means of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th. ſo that it wou'd be almoſt endleſs, to enumerate every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
            <p>In the year 1549 there were no leſs then 200. Miniſters baniſhed, out of this Kingdom, and the Baron of <hi>Schanow</hi> becauſe a <hi>Lutheran,</hi> but under the pretence of a Conſpiracy, was laid upon the Rack, but he magnanimouſly cut out his own Tongue, and being asked the reaſon, he wrote, that it was leſt the torments of the Rack, ſhould make him ſpeak falſly againſt himſelf or others.</p>
            <p>In the year 1617. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second, being obtruded upon by the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> he ſiding with the Papiſts raiſed up a very great perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Proteſtants, which was the cauſe of Electing <hi>Frederick
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106662:6"/>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and the cauſe of all thoſe Wars and embroylments: In which ſuffered many a godly Miniſter, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy pious and harmleſs men, by the ſapiſtical Souldiers, with that barbarous cruelty, that Chriſtian Ears cannot hear, nor Tongue relate, without indignation and abhorrency. For ſome of them were ſtoned to death, others hanged upon a beam, with a ſoft fire made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, roſted to death, others cut peace-meal. And one Miniſter they laid on his back, &amp; ramming his mouth full of Compowder ſet fire to it, and blew his head all to peeces. Another they hanged up by the privy Members, being 70. years old, and burnt his own books under him, and at laſt ſhot him, after he had endured a world of torment and pain.</p>
            <p>In the year 1621. all the Miniſters were baniſhed out of <hi>Prague,</hi> and out of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and all the provinces thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing; never more to return, and made it death to harbour or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal any one of them. Alſo at <hi>Cuttenburg</hi> 21. Miniſters were baniſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame time. <hi>Anno</hi> 1624. a Popiſh Captain cauſed a Miniſters hand firſt to be ſtricken off, and then his head, his bowels to be taken forth, and wrapt in his ſhirt, and his 4. quarters to be ſet on 4 ſtakes, and his head on another. At that time alſo 50. of the Nobility were condemned, ſome to death, ſome to perpetual baniſhment, and ſome to perpetual Impriſonment, 27. were executed, ſome of their right hands and heads, were hung upon the Tower of the Bridge, who all dyed with great conſtancy of minde, and fervency of ſpirit, ſealing to the Proteſtant cauſe with their blood, whoſe heads were afterwards ſolemnly buried, by <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus,</hi> King of <hi>Sweden.</hi> Next came forth an Edict to baniſh all the Proteſtants, and to take away the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from them, that they might be bred in the Romiſh Religion. And then another to baniſh all the Wives of ſuch as were Catholicks from their Husbands, unleſs they would turn. Then they enacted that thoſe who were not Catholicks, ſhould be prohibited all traffick, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with them. There was hardly a City or Town, that eſcaped their barbarous cruelties. And at <hi>Prachatice</hi> they ſlew the <hi>Major,</hi> and 1600 men women and children, letting their bodys lye unburied, for divers days in the dirt and mire, and all the remainders they caſt into priſons, keeping them in a miſerable condition, ſeveral Months. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and godly Books, were prohibited, alſo marriages, and burials, and Baptiſm, deny'd all ſuch as would not turn Catholicks. Some were thruſt into Cellars, and holes full of Snakes and Toads, and ſuch like creatures. Others into places full of ſpikes, ſo that they could neither ſit nor ſtand. Others into narrow places over water, ſo that if they but moved their bodys they would fall into the water: others they gag'd, and thruſt the hoſt down their throats, others again were beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en on the calves of their legs, till they could not ſtand, but fall down on their knees, that they might adore the Hoſt. And thus much for their cruelties acted on this Stage.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:106662:7"/>
            <p>The next Theater,<note place="margin">The perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, in <hi>Germany,</hi> by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts. Out of D. <hi>Vincents</hi> Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> where we may behold theſe ſort of people, act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their bloody parts is <hi>Germany;</hi> miſerably torn and rent to pieces, by their doings, and endeavours to extinguiſh the light of the Goſpel, ſhining forth through <hi>Luther,</hi> and others then ſtirred up by God, to perfect the work of Reformation. This perſecution began <hi>Anno Chriſti,</hi> 1523. by the Popes ſtirring up the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Proteſtants as Hereticks, allowing him 200000 Crowns to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the raiſing Soldiers for that end, with an engagement alſo, to raiſe at his own coſt 12000 foot, and 600 Horſe. Thus he began with the ſword, that he might end with the fagot. The Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> aud the <hi>Lantgrave</hi> ſtand up for the Proteſtants, and are taken priſoners 1547. and whereever they got the day, all ſorts of Cruelties, murthers, torments, racks, ſire and fagot followed: So that all <hi>Germany</hi> was at once in a flame, and combuſtion, and in a moſt miſerable condition, flying and dying in all places, for their Conſcience, and Religion. At <hi>Meldrop</hi> they took the Miniſter, a godly man, out of his bed, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him to go many miles on foot, in froſt and ſnow upon the ce, bare-footed, and bare-legg'd, beating, cutting and flaſhing him, and pricking him with halberds, and at laſt they barbarouſly roaſted him on coals to death, his name was <hi>Sutphen.</hi> At <hi>Vienna</hi> many were drowned, and put to ſeveral ſorts of death. At the ſacking of <hi>Miltenburg,</hi> many ſuffer'd; one Miniſter they hung up by the hands, with a mighty ſtone faſtned to his ſeet where he remained 6 hours in that great torment. Death was accounted a mercy, and hanging they thought to eaſie a puniſhment: At <hi>Schalt,</hi> at <hi>Merſpurg,</hi> and <hi>Munchen,</hi> and ſeveral other places, the rage of their malice and ſpite was ſhown, in putting to death many poor Souls. At <hi>Paſewalk</hi> they committed many villanies, raviſhing the women, deſlouring the maids, killing the men, burning the houſes, and ſmothering the children with ſtraw, ſet on fire in the cellers, whether they had crept for ſafety. At <hi>Mudenburg</hi> they did the like 1631, where they burnt the whole City to aſhes, and where they put at leaſt 20000 perſons to death, 6000 were drowned in the River <hi>Elb.</hi> Ladys and Gentlewomen were yoaked together like beaſts, and ſo turned out to the woods, where they were raviſhed and abuſed, and then had their hair and ears cropt off, and disfigured. At <hi>Hocſter</hi> 1634, they ſpared none, neither man, woman nor child, but put all to ſword, and then threw their bodys into the <hi>Weſer.</hi> At <hi>Grippenbourg</hi> they tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the Senators, and chief of the place to death, with ſmoak and ſtarving. At <hi>Heildeburg</hi> they ſhut up in priſon a great many Miniſters, ſeeding them only with bread and water. At <hi>Frankendale,</hi> contrary to agreement, and Articles, they put many to death, and others to unreaſonable ranſoms. In <hi>Saxony,</hi> they tortured the Proteſtants, by preſſing their Thumbs between wheels. In <hi>Pomeren,</hi> they forced them to eat their own excrements, and if they refuſed them, they thruſt them down their throats till they were choaked. Some they tormented
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106662:7"/>with cords about their heads, till they twiſted their eyes out, and that the blood run out at their ears, noſes, and mouths. To others they tyed burning matches between their fingers, yea to their eyes, ears, noſes, tongues, cheeks, breaſts, legs, and ſecret parts. Yea they cram'd the ſecret parts of ſeveral women with gunpowder; and ſo ſetting fire to it, blew up their bellies and wombs, moſt barbarouſly. Others they tormented with Bodkins, and Knives, and to ſome they made holes thorow the ſleſhy part of their Armes, thighs, and Legs, and ſo thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cords thorow them, tormented them after that faſhion. Some they hung up in the ſmoak, drying them with ſmall fires, and ſometimes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them ſmall drink, or water to refreſh them, that they might not dye too ſoon, and be freed from their torments. Some they roaſted with fire made of ſtraw, others had their hands and feet bound ſo hard, till the blood ſprung forth of the ends of their fingers, and toes. Some had their hands and feet bound backwards together, and their mouths ſtopped with rags, to hinder them from praying. And ſeveral they hung up by their privy parts: They plained the faces of others with Chiſels, others they cauſed to draw on boots, filled with ſcalding Oyl, and ſo roaſted their legs over the fire. Some they gelt in the preſence of their wives and Children: Others had their bodys hung up by cords, and every joynt diſlocated by tying of weights to their ſeveral limbs. Some were gag'd, and with Tunnels had ſtinking water and piſs powred down their throats, till their bellies ſwelled like Tuns, whereby they dyed with moſt horrid torment. Then they thruſt down the throats of ſome knotted clouts, with a ſtring faſtened to them, whereby they pull'd them out again, and puting them to miſerable torment, by miſplacing their bowels, that many became blinde, dumb, deaf, and lame for ever. Some they ſawed off their legs alive, one Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter they bound upon a Table, and placing a great Cat upon his bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo provoked the Cat, that ſhe ſcratched his guts forth of his belly, with its teeth and nails, till he dyed. At <hi>Madenburg,</hi> they raviſhed the wife and daughters of one of the Miniſters before his face, and tore from the Mothers breaſt a ſucking infant, and ſtuck it on the top of a Lance, and after they had made him ſee all this, they brought him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtreet, and burnt him with his own Books. Yea ſuch was the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable beaſtlineſs commited at this time, that no pen can write it. In <hi>Pomeren</hi> they made the Parents ſing Pſalms, whilſt they raviſhed their daughters before their faces. Nay they ſpared not their dead Corpſes, but lay with the women after they had out their throats: At <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Friburg,</hi> and other places they did the like, eating the young children, and wearing the noſes, and ears, as a bravery in their Caps.</p>
            <p>Thus theſe Maſſacres, and bloody Murthers defiled the whole Land, and <hi>Germany</hi> groaned under the oppreſſion, till the peace of <hi>Munſter,</hi> and <hi>Oſnaburg</hi> 1648. which put a ſtop to the Perſecution, they being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to it, by Gods bringing in the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> who over-run <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106662:8"/>and revived the cauſe of the Proteſtants,<note place="margin">As alſo in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </note> almoſt overthrown by ſo many thouſand perſecutions.</p>
            <p>Theſe bloody Tyrants, vented their rage and fury, not only in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> but alſo in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and other parts: they committed there alſo the ſame Tragedys where they had any power, and the Miniſters were generally baniſhed, and put to death, and the ſame picture of their cruelties, which you have had repreſented to you in <hi>Germany,</hi> might have been acted over again in this Kingdom, but we have not room at this time for the like relation; only one new ſort of death read of, uſed to a Miniſter in <hi>Hungary</hi> by tying about his naked body, Hens, Geeſe, Ducks, and Hares, and ſo ſeting dogs upon them, baited him to death, tearing and renting his fleſh, till he dyed.</p>
            <p>Their rage in the Low Countrys,<note place="margin">The Low Countrys. Hiſt. of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands.</hi> and <hi>Slei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>Netherlands</hi> was no leſs, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but fire, and fagot among them, by which ſuffered many a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and Godly perſon, of every Age, and Sex, as well in <hi>Holland,</hi> as elſe where.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Antwerp,</hi> one <hi>Nicholas</hi> a pious holy man, was bound up in a ſack and ſo drowned.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Holland, Piſtorius</hi> was burnt, being carryed to the ſtake, with a fools Coat on his back, and alſo a widdow called <hi>Wendelmuta,</hi> who ſhewed much conſtancy.</p>
            <p>Several Miniſters were beheaded, among the reſt one <hi>George Scherter,</hi> who ſome time after he was beheaded, his body lying on the belly, turned himſelf on the back, and croſſing the right foot over the left, and his right hand over the left, ſo continued, to the great admiration of the ſpectators, and the converſion of many.</p>
            <p>Several were drowned, others made away in Priſons, others ſhut up in dark and noyſome places, and none ſuffer'd to come at them, fed only with bread and water, till they were famiſh'd.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Lovain,</hi> ſeveral were Martyr'd, ſome by fire, others beheaded.</p>
            <p>In the years 1543. and 1544. There was a very great perſecution all over <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſo that there was neither Town, nor city, in all the Country, wherein ſome were not baniſhed, beheaded, or condemned to perpetual Impriſonment, neither was there any reſpect to either Age, or Sex: But eſpecially at <hi>Gaunt,</hi> many of the chief men were burned for Religion, The like was in <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Artois,</hi> inſomuch that 200. men and women, were made away at one time, ſome drowned, ſome buried quick, and ſome privily Murthered, ſo that the hands of the hangmen begun to be tyred, and weary with Executions.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Delden,</hi> at <hi>echlin,</hi> at <hi>Dornic,</hi> ſeveral were put to death, among the reſt two Noble Virgins ſiſters, and one Mother, and her 3. Sons, who all dyed owning the Goſpel, and exclaming againſt the cruelty of the Papiſts.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time they miſerably puniſhed one <hi>Bertand,</hi> for tramp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the hoſt under his feet, in his zeal, by tormenting him thrice up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106662:8"/>the Rack, and then becauſe he would not recant, in the market place of <hi>Lornick,</hi> they put a ball of ron into his mouth, to keep him from ſpeaking, and then cruſhed his right hand betwixt two flat red hot rons, till the form of his hand was changed; and after that, they did the like by his right foot, which he enduring with admirable patience, taking the Ball of iron out of his mouth, they cut out his Tongue, and then thruſt in the Ball again; then tying him with a chain about the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, with a pully, hoiſted him up, and making a fire underneath, let him down by degrees into the fire, and ſo continued hoiſting him up, and letting him down, till he dyed, and was burnt to aſhes, which they caſt into the River.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Valence</hi> alſo, ſeveral were executed, and alſo at <hi>Liſle,</hi> where one of the Judges pronouncing the ſentence of condemnation, ſaid, <hi>This day you ſhall go to dwell with all the Devills in hell-fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the great inſtrument of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſecution, in theſe Countrys, was the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> who boaſted, that beſides thoſe he had ſlain in the wars, he had put into the hand of the Common Hangman, to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, within the ſpace of ſix years, no leſs than 18000. perſons, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting his Soldiers to raviſh honeſt matrons, and virgins, and many times cauſing their parents, and husbands, to ſtand by and behold it.</p>
            <p>His Son <hi>Don Frederick</hi> following his Fathers Steps, committed many cruelties, and at <hi>Zutphen</hi> he hang'd, drown'd and murther'd a great number of the inhabitants, ſhewing infinite cruelties upon their wives, and Virgins, not ſparing the very Infants; and alſo in <hi>Naerden</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> where entering the Town without reſiſtance, he committed ſuch abominable Cruelties, that never <hi>Turks, Seythians,</hi> or the moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, and inhumane Nations in the World, exceeded them. Here treacherouſly he commanded all the Burgers, and chief of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, to aſſemble themſelves together, that he might acquaint them with ſome Orders, and when they were all aſſembled together, in the Chappell of the HOſpital, he commanded his Soldiers to murther them all, without ſparing any one. The men were all ſlain, and the women of the Town firſt raviſhed, and then barbarouſly murthered, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and infants had their Throats out, ſo that the whole Town was deſtroyed; and neither man, wife, maid nor child, young, nor old, ſpared, and the Town was raſed without pitty, or mercy.</p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Don Frederick,</hi> at <hi>Herlem,</hi> exerciſed the like perfidiouſneſs; for when they had been forced to deliver up their Town, through Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, having eat for hunger, bread made with linſeed and turneps, and lived upon Horſes, Dogs, and cats, they made a compoſition, by which they paid 240000 <hi>florins</hi> to redeem their Town from ſpoil, yet being entred, according to that wicked Principle of theirs, that no faith is to be kept with Hereticks, he commanded all the Towns-men to bring in their arms, and to aſſemble themſelves in the Cloyſter of <hi>Zyel,</hi> and all the women in the Cathedral, and all the Soldiers into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106662:9"/>Church, where he made his Soldiers guard them, whilſt the perſidious Spanyards plundred their Houſes: The next day he cauſed 300 Walloons to be hanged, and beheaded, and two hundred and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeven Soldiers more to be drowned, in the <hi>Mcre</hi> at <hi>Harlem.</hi> The day following 300. Soldiers and Burgers, loſt their heads, and the next day many more, and ſeveral Miniſters: and alſo all the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> they could finde, and to fill up the Sea of blood, all the ſick and wounded were beheaded at the door of the <hi>Hoſpital.</hi> And a party of Soldiers that were in an out-Sconce were all ſtarved to death.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Valenciennes</hi> they hang'd up all the <hi>French</hi> Soldiers, all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and miniſters they could take in the Town, and conſiſcated all their goods which amounted to a great vallue.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Antwerp</hi> they drowned one <hi>John de Boſcane</hi> a Proteſtant in a Tub of water, and becauſe he was tall, and the tub of the ſhorteſt, ſo that they could not ſtifle him, they ſtab'd him with daggers, and ſo both kill'd and drowned him at once. In the ſame place abundance more were martyr'd for the Truth, and cleaving to their Religion, embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed death cheerfully.</p>
            <p>Alſo at <hi>Breda</hi> divers ſuffered for the ſame cauſe, and indeed all <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> over, their dead Bodies being caſt forth, to be gazed on in every place; and multitudes, both men and women, were impriſoned for their belief and Conſcience. In the City of <hi>Valence,</hi> they executed 57. perſons, moſt of them Burgeſſes, only becauſe they profeſſed the true Faith of Jeſus Chriſt, and diſſented from the Religion of the Papiſts.</p>
            <p>And to conclude the ſad Cataſtrophe,<note place="margin">Strada.</note> we may alſo remember, that Prince <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> was ſhot by a villain cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Joanville,</hi> encouraged thereto by a <hi>Jacobine</hi> Friar, who was hang'd for the Fact, though it proved not mortal. But that attempt not being enough to ſatisfie theſe blood-ſuckers, and Prince-killers, they hired one <hi>Gerard</hi> a <hi>Burgundian,</hi> who taking better aim, ſhot this Prince, the head of the proteſtants, ſo that he dyed immediatly, as he was coming from dinner at <hi>Delf</hi> in <hi>Holland;</hi> 1584.</p>
            <p>Let us now ſtept into <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>France.</hi> Hiſtr of <hi>France,</hi> Hiſt. of the Tragical Maſſacres in <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> and ſee whether the goſpel has any free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome there, from their perſecutions, you will then behold the ſame picture of cruelty, murther and Blood; they change not their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with the aire of the Country, they are not bloody and cruel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are <hi>Spanyards,</hi> but becauſe they are <hi>Papiſts,</hi> tis infuſed into them by the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and as principles of their Religion, and not ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into them from without, they are the ſame in <hi>France,</hi> as elſewhere, bloody and murtherous perſecutors of ſuch as fall not down and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Idoll of their ſetting up: meer <hi>Nebuchadnezzars,</hi> and cruel Tyrants.</p>
            <p>They began there ill the year 1209. with ſeveral learned and good men at <hi>Paris,</hi> who diſſenting in ſome points were burnt.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Metz</hi> in <hi>Lorraine,</hi> for profeſſing the Goſpel, and throwing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106662:9"/>down ſome Images, they cauſed one <hi>John Clark</hi> who denyed not the fact, to have his right hand cut off, his noſe to be pulled from his Face, with ſnarp pincers, and his arms and breaſts pulled off by the ſome inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then caſt into the fire, and conſumed to aſhes.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Paris,</hi> at <hi>Melda,</hi> in <hi>Limoſine,</hi> at <hi>Fountains, Rutiers, Roan, Troyes, Bourdeaux, St. Michael, Lions, Meaux,</hi> and <hi>Fera,</hi> and in ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, a great number were burnt, rack'd, whipt, beaten, and divers ways tormented to death; at laſt they made a Law, that all that were condemned to be burnt, if they recanted not at the ſtake, ſhould have their tongues cut out, that they might not with their holy and dying ſpeeches, move others. And this was dilligently obſerved.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Paris</hi> one <hi>Florent Venote</hi> a Miniſter, was impriſoned in ſo narrow a place, that he could neither ſtand nor lye in it, in which they kept him 7. weeks, whereas there was never a malefactor that could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it 15 days without growing mad or dying. Afterwards they cut out his Tongue, and laſtly was ſo mercifull as to execute him.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> another of the Popes Inſtruments of perſecution, upon the <hi>Hugonots</hi> as they call the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in thoſe parts, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with his Soldiers, many bloody and barbarous murthers, among the reſt at <hi>Veſſy,</hi> he put ſeveral hundreds to death, of men, women and children, that were aſſembled to hear a Sermon, mangling their Limbs, and ſtrewing them about the ſeats and galleries of the Church.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Sentis</hi> many ſuffer'd, ſome were beheaded, ſome murther'd, ſome whipt, ſome beaten, and ſent to the Gallies, not ſparing the ſimple women. And the ſame alſo at <hi>Charlons,</hi> where they tortur'd one <hi>Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier</hi> a miniſter, by ſtraining his thumbs with a ſmall cord, till the blood came out at the ends of them, being ſo tyed faſt behind his back, with another Rope they hoiſt him up by the Thumbs, twitching him up and down, then tying great ſtones to his great Toes, let him hang ſo till his Spirits failed him; and then ſuddenly looſing the rope, let him fall with all the weights on his face upon the hard floor, and then caſting him into priſon, would not let him have the benefit of a Chirurgion, with which barbarous uſage, being above 50 years old, he not long after dyed.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Amiens,</hi> all the Bibles, Teſtaments, and Pſalm-books were burnt, and the miniſters Pulpit, with divers perſons, men and women. At <hi>Abbeville</hi> they ſlew the Lord of <hi>Harcourt,</hi> and dragged ſome along the ſtreets with their faces in the kennell. At <hi>Meaux</hi> there were about 400. of the religious Citizens ſlain, beſides a 1000. villanies committed, the women, and maids raviſhed openly in the ſtreets, and market-place; men, women, and children maſſacred, ſome forced to be remarried, and others to be rebabtized. The very Prieſts ſlaying divers with their own hands. At <hi>Bar</hi> the ſame cruelties and murthers were committed, if not worſe, for ſome pulled out the hearts of theſe poor wretches, and moſt inhumanely gnawed them with their teeth, rejoycing that they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106662:10"/>taſted of an <hi>Hugenots</hi> Heart. At <hi>Sens</hi> an hundred proteſtants were bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly maſſacred, and their naked bodies thrown into the River, their houſes plundered and then burnt, together with the Church. At <hi>Crant</hi> the like, many murthered. At <hi>Auxerre</hi> the like. At <hi>Nevers,</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillen</hi> the like horrid murthers were committed, where they left no manner of cruelty unacted, neither upon women, or Children, old nor young, not ſparing the children in their mothers bellies, but rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them out and daſhing their brains againſt the pavement. At <hi>Guyen</hi> they uſed all the cruelties could be invented, where ſome <hi>Italians</hi> cut a child in two, and eat the Liver in hatred to its Religion. At <hi>Montar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis</hi> they committed many outrages againſt thoſe of the Religion, and had done more but that they were oppoſed by the Lady <hi>Rene,</hi> Daughter of King <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>12th,</hi> and Dutcheſs Dowager of <hi>Ferrara.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Monlins</hi> many ſuffered: At <hi>Mans</hi> 200. men, women, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were put to death; and ſuch as fled, had their houſes pillaged, and were executed in Effigy, and their children made incapable of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heriting their goods or lands. Above 120. men, women, and children, Murthered in the Neighbour-Villages, ſome hang'd, ſome beheaded, ſome drowned: And one Captain flung above 50. perſons into his fiſh-ponds, to feed his pikes, and as many more were drowned in the ditches.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Angers</hi> they committed the like cruelties, and above 80. perſons executed at one time, and an aged Gentlewoman of above 70. years of age, beaten to death with piſtols. And one Gentleman they broke upon a Croſs, and ſo left him hanging, with many other unſpeakable Villanies. At <hi>Liguel</hi> they did the like, putting out the Miniſters eyes, and then burning him with a ſmall fire. The Village of <hi>Aze</hi> they burnt to the ground, drowned the Miniſter of 70. years old, and Maſſacred 30. perſons. In <hi>Tours</hi> they Murthered an 140. and caſt them into the river, ſparing not ſo much as the preſident, becauſe he favour'd them, for after they had beaten him with ſtaves, and ſtript him to his ſhirt, they hang'd him up by one leg, with his head downwards in the water, up to the breaſt, and whilſt he was yet living, they ript up his belly, pluckt out his guts, and ſlung them into the river, and ſticking his heart on a Lance, they carryed it about, ſaying, <hi>This is the heart of the Preſident of the Hugonots.</hi> Shortly after ſome hundreds of the richeſt and beſt ſort of Citizens were murthered, the Duke of <hi>Monpenſieur</hi> ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up Gibbets, ſtakes, and wheels in all places, to execute them on, and when any man, or woman was put to death, they entred their houſes, Murther'd their Children, and took all their goods.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Ponteale Mer</hi> was alſo uſed all kinds of cruelties, and where many ſuffered. And at <hi>Roan</hi> many hundreds ſuffer'd, among the reſt 3. Councellors were hanged, and the Town ſack'd for 4. moneths toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; at <hi>Vire, Valougnes, Agen,</hi> and <hi>Remes,</hi> ſuch horrid cruelties were acted as I am weary to relate, and ſuch beaſtiality uſed towards the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106662:10"/>women, as cannot in modeſty be ſet down. In the laſt of theſe places, there was 500. hang'd upon Gibbets, among whom was a grave Conn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor in his gown and ſquare Cap: one poor man they mangled, and cut his body, and fill'd all his wounds with ſalt.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Blois</hi> ſeveral were executed, among the reſt ſeveral women flung into the river, and if any came to ſhore by ſwiming, they were thruſt back with pikes, and halberts. At <hi>Guil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> they flung many from the top of a Rock, upon other under-lying rocks, by which their bodies were torn to peeces.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Souraize</hi> many periſhed with ſeveral tortures, among which one woman had her mouth forc'd open with a dagger, and cramm'd with lime and then piſs poured down her throat, and beſides uſed very cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly, by beating, and with cords. Another man one <hi>Peter Roche</hi> they cauſed to dig his own grave, and to go into it, to ſee how it would fit him, and then buried him alive. At <hi>Marſans</hi> they rowned one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with Thorns, then whip'd her, and laſtly ſtoned her to death. The like they did by another called <hi>Janctta Calvin.</hi> In <hi>Mont de Martin</hi> they put ſeveral to death, and buried one quick. In <hi>Tholouſe</hi> was a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great maſſacre, there being in that City at leaſt 30000 Proteſtants, ſo that the River was cover'd o're with the Bodies of the ſlain. In <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moux,</hi> all the cruelties and villanies that could be deviſed, were acted, and alſo at <hi>Carcaſſon,</hi> and at <hi>Nonnay</hi> where they knocked out the brains of a naylor upon his own Anvill, becauſe he would not give himſelf to the Devill, ſeveral thrown from an high Tower; others drag'd about the ſtreets, and ſtab'd: wives and virgins openly raviſhed. At <hi>Foix, Aurange, Grenoble, Ciſterno, Beaune,</hi> and <hi>Maſcon,</hi> were no leſs (all partaking of the general calamity) than all the fore-rehearſed villanies committed, in as barbarous a manner; ſo that all <hi>France</hi> reaked with the blood of the Innoeent, and their goar defiled all the Land.</p>
            <p>But to conclude this Tragical Scene, we will now end with the great and notorious maſſacre of <hi>Paris,</hi> at the end of the Civill war of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>24. 1522.</hi> Thuanus.</note> which happened upon that unholy League between the <hi>Pope,</hi> the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the <hi>Guiſes.</hi> Peace being ſeemingly concluded, between the Leaguers, and the Proteſtant party, and all differences ended, and adjuſted, though through the private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigations and councells of the Queen mother, nothing leſs was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the marriage betwixt the King of <hi>Navar</hi> and the Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> the Kings Siſter, being made the ſtale to draw all the Heads of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant party into the Net, and with the Heart and Soul of them (as they called) <hi>Coligny</hi> Admiral of <hi>France,</hi> to out off all the reſt. The plot was laid, and with great artice and diſſimulation, the chief of all the Proteſtant NObility in the Kingdome, are drawn without ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Paris,</hi> to aſſiſt at theſe Nuptials, invited by the King, with all amicable ſignes of Love, Peace, and kindneſs. <hi>Coligny</hi> among the reſt though diſſwaded by many of his Friends, would not ſeem to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106662:11"/>the Kings kindneſs and Royal word. But at the time appointed, which was at the tolling of the Palace bell before day, in the morning, all things being before prepared, and ordered by the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and bloody inſtruments, the Maſſacre begun, the Papiſts diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing themſelves, by hankerchiefs on their Armes, and white Croſſes in their hats. The Admiral <hi>Coligny</hi> was the firſt they ſet upon and Murther'd, and then the reſt of the Proteſtant Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, who were moſt lodged in a quarter together, and then through the whole City, where ever they could finde them, ſo that there was nothing but blood, horror, death, murthering, and ſlaying through that great City, at which time fell by this barbarous means 10000 Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. The body of that Noble Admiral they drag'd about the ſtreets, having cut off his hands, and head, which was ſent as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Pope at <hi>Rome,</hi> and then hung it on a Gibbet, and making a fire under it, uſed it with all the diſpight imaginable. But this was not enough to ſatiate, and glut their bloody mindes, immediately the King cauſes Letters, to be ſent away poſt, through all his Kingdome, to the chief Citys, and Towns to do the like. And pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently all <hi>France</hi> is filled with Murthers, and ſlaughters, and the Earth is bathed with the blood of the <hi>Hugonots:</hi> In ſome places more, in ſome leſs, as the Governors, and Magiſtrates were more or leſs cruelly, and popiſhly affected. At <hi>Meaux,</hi> at <hi>Troys,</hi> at <hi>Orliance,</hi> at <hi>Roan, Burdeaux, Tholouſe, Angiers, Lions,</hi> and ſeveral other Cities, Towns, Villages, and places, nothing but Maſſacres, flaughters, Murthers, blood, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and cruelties were enacted: ſo that the dead Corps in every place lay like dung on the face of the Earth, and they gathered the fat and greeſe of men, and women, ſold it about at 3 <hi>s.</hi> the pound, the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers were peſtered with carcaſſes thrown into them; and nothing but horror and confuſion, reigned in all places. So that at that time by computation at leaſt 30000 fell, beſides thoſe in <hi>Paris,</hi> but ſome rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon more, for the King himſelf confeſt he had a liſt of 7000. ſlain, as <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carela</hi> relates, <hi>in vita Greg.</hi> 13. And of all this blood, and Murthers, and Maſſacres, the Popes Legat publiquely abſolved them, who were the chief Actors in it.</p>
            <p>We will not after this, mention to you the ſiege of <hi>Sancre,</hi> 1573 in which the poor Proteſtants, were fain to eat Dogs, Cats, Rats, Mice, Moles, Horſe hoofs, Hornes, Lanthorns, Calves, and Sheep-skins, Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, and all their furniture for their horſes, and one eat the head and brains of his own daughter, that dyed for famine, nor the ſeige of <hi>Rochel,</hi> 1575. in which they endured famine, miſery, and hardſhip, nor of the ſeige of the ſame place, in the year 1628. in which alſo the famine was ſo great, that they eat the very buttocks of the dead, and at the taking it, a buſhel of Wheat was ſold for 20 <hi>l.</hi> a pound of bread 20 <hi>s.</hi> a quarter of Mutton, 6 <hi>l.</hi> a pound of Butter, 30 <hi>s.</hi> an Egg, 8 <hi>s.</hi> an ounce of Sugar, 2 <hi>s</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> a dry'd Fiſh, 20 <hi>s.</hi> a pint of <hi>French</hi> Wine, 20 <hi>s.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106662:11"/>a pint of Milk, 30 <hi>s.</hi> a pound of Grapes 3 <hi>s. &amp;c.</hi>— Nor ſpeak of the perſecutions of the Proteſtants ſince, by pulling down their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, grievous fines, impriſonments, and baniſhment, being ſtill wearied and oppreſſed, groaning under the yoak of their <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage. I am almoſt weary with writing, and perhaps thou art with reading, theſe Maſſacres, and ſlaughters, therefore I will here mention no more, but briefly proceed.</p>
            <p>We will now leave the Kingdome of the moſt Chriſtian King;<note place="margin">Spain.</note> and paſſing over the <hi>Pyrennes,</hi> ſee if the Goſpel can have any harbour,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gonſalvus Montanus</hi> Diſcovery of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs.</note> or its profeſſors peace in that of the moſt Catholick King. But alas! the ſame Tyrannic cruelty if not worſe, we ſhall finde exerciſed againſt all that diſſent from the Church of <hi>Rome. Spain</hi> cannot afford ſo many Martyrs as <hi>France,</hi> becauſe there the profeſſors of the Goſpell were but few, being kept from thence by the terror of the Inquiſition. They have been here ſo carefull as to cruſh all appearance of the Goſpell in the Bud, and ſuch care and inſpection is taken, and ſuch diligent ſearch made, and ſuch horrid puniſhments inflicted, by theſe inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that it is almoſt impoſſible, any Proteſtant ſhould be in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Spain,</hi> and not to be found out and puniſhed. Yet in the year 1545. ſeveral Proteſtants at St. <hi>Lucar, Validolid, Siril,</hi> and other places in <hi>Spain</hi> ſuffer'd death, 30 at one time, and 1550 man more. There were <hi>Francis Romanes, Rochus Calculla</hi> a Doctor, <hi>John Pontio, Gonſalvo</hi> a Prieſt, <hi>Juliano, Leon, Arias Loſada,</hi> a Phyſitian, with a Lady and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral women, and Virgins, burnt at ſeveral times, in ſeveral places, and 20. others in one fire, after they had endured all the horrid torments of the Rack, the Pully, the Trough, the Barnacle, the twiſting Cord, and the like horrid inventions of tortures, in the Priſon of the inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Burton, Bakere, Burgat, Burges,</hi> and <hi>Hooker,</hi> Engliſhmen, were there burnt, and horridly tormented, by theſe curſed Inquiſitors, who have their Agents in every corner, to finde out and betray all ſuch, as they have but the leaſt ſuſpition of, for favoring Hereticks as they call Proteſtants: Theſe Agents they name <hi>Familiars,</hi> who like ſpirits inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate into the boſome of people, to deceive and betray them, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Flys,</hi> who are alſo buſy in taking up ſuch, as their <hi>Familiars</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray. So that by theſe cruelties ſubtle arts, and ſly practiſes, they have ſtifled the Proteſtant Faith in <hi>Spain,</hi> and though there are privately many who own the truth, they are forced to keep it ſo private, as ſcarce to communicate their minds, to a Brother, or a Siſter, for fear of the torments of the Inquiſition, which is much more feared then death.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Portugal</hi> is but a little Kingdome,<note place="margin">Portugal.</note> and the power of the Pope and his Inſtruments great there, as well as in <hi>Spain,</hi> they have mightyly ſuppreſt the truth with their tortures, yet ſome have there alſo ſuffer'd, and among others, one <hi>William Gardner,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, whom they put to death with moſt exquiſit torments at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> 1552.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106662:12"/>
            <p>We will paſs over the <hi>Alpes</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Italy.</note> which being ſo neer the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Inſpection of the Pope, we may well ſuppoſe it does not har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour many Proteſtants, at leaſt ſuch as dare appear to be ſuch, and to own the profeſſion publiquely, by reaſon of the ſame ſtrict Court of Inquiſition,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clerks</hi> Martyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</note> at firſt inſtituted againſt the Moors and Jews, in <hi>Spain,</hi> and now uſed only for the finding out of good <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and for their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and puniſhment; yet there have been ſeverall that have owned the Goſpell, even in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, and in ſeverall Cittys of <hi>Italy,</hi> and have ſealed their profeſſion with their Blood; as <hi>Arnold</hi> of <hi>Brixia, Fannius</hi> at <hi>Ferrara, Dominicus</hi> at <hi>Placentia, Gelacius Tricius</hi> at St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelo, John Mollins</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> 1553. <hi>Francis Gamba</hi> at <hi>Milan, Algerius</hi> at <hi>Padua,</hi> 1555, <hi>Aloyſins</hi> at <hi>Rome, Bovellus</hi> at the ſame place, all mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred for their Faith. Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> raiſed up a very hot perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in all the Terriitorys of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein many ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And it grew ſo hot in the year 1560. in the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> that many noble men, and their wives, and divers others were ſlain and butchered: 88. at one time, being thurſt up in a cloſe pen, and one by one being taken forth, and being blindfolded, and led a little way from the place, the executioner commanded them to kneel down, and ſo cut their throats one after another, like ſheep, leaving them half dead on the ground, returning with the bloody knife in his mouth; and muffler in his hand, goes to the reſt, till he had cut all their throats. This was in <hi>Calabria,</hi> 1560.</p>
            <p>The City of <hi>Venice</hi> kept it ſelf free for a long time,<note place="margin">Venice.</note> from this plague of the Inquiſition, till the year 1542, at which time the Pope ſo far prevailed, as to ſet up there the Inquiſition, and then began a terrible perſecution, wherein many a ſervant of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſuffer'd; Here they found out a new way of murthering them that they condemned to dye, which was accounted the more merecifull Judgment, than their Racking, whipping, beating, and water torments, they faſtned and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron Chain about their middles, with a very heavy ſtone tyed at it, then were they laid upon a plank, between two <hi>Gondelo's,</hi> or ſmall boats, and rowed to an appointed place in the Sea, where the boats parting aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, they immediately ſunk to the bottom and were drowned. In the year 1566. a miniſter, and many others, ſuffer'd after this manner, and divers ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> where they ended their days by ſlaughter, or elſe more miſerably, in ſtinking and naſty dungeons, not being permitted to have any thing to lye on but ſtraw. About that time ſuffer'd alſo at <hi>Venice</hi> by drowning <hi>Anthony Bicetto, Francis Spinola, Sega,</hi> and others. And 1595. a young Engliſhman at <hi>Rome,</hi> whom they uſed cruelly, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving led him from the Capitol, his upper parts naked, on his head a cap, made in ſhape of a devil, his Breeches painted like Hell-fire, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills in it, and thus being brought to the place of execution, they cut off his right hand, alive, and becauſe he began to praiſe God, they gagged him, and then ſeared all his fleſh with hot Irons, and at laſt burnt him at the Stake.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106662:12"/>
            <p>It is not the Rocks nor the faſtneſſes of the <hi>Alpes</hi> that can keep out this monſter of perſecution, he even aſcends thoſe precipices,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toline.</note> and in the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> or the Country of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> he ſcratches graves for the faithfull with his murtherous Claws. There had been for a long time, a free exerciſe of the Religion, which invited many to fly into thoſe mountains for ſafety, but when the power of <hi>Rome</hi> got among them, it made an horrible ſlaughter, and a bloody edict was procured, by the Papiſts at <hi>Rome,</hi> for the killing, and murthering all the Proteſtants, in thoſe parts, and which was ſoon and cruelly executed at <hi>Tel. Tyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, Bruſe, Sondres, Malenco, Caſpano, Trahen,</hi> and other Towns in the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> where a very great company of all Sects, Ages, and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, were as barbarouſly uſed, and there murthered, as in any other place, and this in the year 1620. Many were drowned in the River <hi>Alba,</hi> and <hi>Adda,</hi> ſome had their Cheeks ſlit up to their ears, ſome ſtrapadoed, others their mouths and ears filled with gunpowder, and ſo fired; others ſlaſh'd, and cut, and ſo miſerably driven to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, others again flung from thoſe high rocks into the deep valleys, and ſo broken to peices, and moſt of them one way or other deſtroy'd, without any commiſeration, or pitty.</p>
            <p>In the Marquiſate of <hi>Saluces</hi> are ſeveral Churches of the Proteſtant Religion, as <hi>Pravillem, Biolts, Bietone, Dronier,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſate of <hi>Saluces.</hi>
               </note> and divers others who liv'd peaceably for a long time, under the Government of <hi>France,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the many attempts of the apiſts againſt them, but after the maſſacre ot <hi>Paris,</hi> the Kings Letters were ſent to the Governour Monſieur <hi>Biragu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to deſtroy them all, but his prudence put a ſtop to it for the preſent, only impriſoning the cheif heads of them, till he had orders for their releaſe; but after this Marquiſate came to the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> he made a cruel edict that all perſons that would not within 15 days, renounce their Religion, and go to Maſs, ſhould depart for ever out of the Marquiſate, giving them only two months time to remove in; upon pain of Death. This was publiſhed 1601. ſo that there was nothing to be ſeen all over the Country, but packing up, and marching away into baniſhment, leaving their Houſes, Fields, and Country, which they had for Ages enjoy'd; ſome retired into <hi>France</hi> beyond the <hi>Alps,</hi> ſome to <hi>Geneva,</hi> and ſome to the <hi>Vallies</hi> of <hi>Piemont,</hi> none being ſuffer'd to ſtay, but ſuch as would ſubmit againſt their Conſciences, to go to maſs and to worſhip Idols: but their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are not free, no place is exempt, where ever the power of this beaſt reigns, as we may behold in the adjoyning Vallies.</p>
            <p>The poor and diſtreſſed Proteſtants, in the Vallies of <hi>Piemont,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emont.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quaſi Pede montium,</hi> at the foot of the mountains of the <hi>Alps,</hi> have been very great ſufferers by the popiſh Tyrany. They are under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and are the offspring of the old <hi>Waldeneſes,</hi> and from that time, profeſſing that Religion, having Evangelical Churches in the ſeveral Vallies of <hi>Angrognia, Bobio, Villaro, Valguic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harda
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106662:13"/>Rora, Tagliaretto, La Ricca, di Boneti, La Torre,</hi> St. <hi>Martino, Dcroſa, Roccapiata, Lucarna,</hi> St <hi>Barthelmo,</hi> in all which the Inhabitants were moſt Proteſtants, and had been long indulged in their Religion by the Princes of <hi>Savoy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Sam. Morlands</hi> Hiſt. of the <hi>Evang</hi> Churches in the valleys of <hi>Piedmont.</hi>
               </note> to whom they were Subjects. But in the year 1565. a cruel edict was publiſhed, that all ſuch as would not comply with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and go to Maſs, within ten days ſhould be baniſhed from their Country and habitation, but by the interceſſion of the King of <hi>France,</hi> and the Elector <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> this Edict was recalled, and they continued quiet till the year 1655, wherein the late great maſſacre was comitted againſt theſe poor men for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion Sake: Though all along the Papiſts had by many cunning plots and contrivances endeavoured their ſubverſion, by endeavouring to ſtir them up to Rebellion, and by planting Colledges of Emiſſaries amongſt them, which like goads in their ſides ſtill annoyed them, and proved a great trouble and affliction to them: always procuring ſome cruel, and harſh edict againſt them, by their complaints, and lyes raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as 1602 an edict for the baniſhing all private, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Proteſtant Schoolmaſters as incendiaries; and 1622. That no ſtrangers either Miniſters, or Schoolmaſters, ſhould be entertained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; 1634 an Edict came out, that all the Proteſtants of <hi>Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piglione,</hi> ſhould be baniſhed: and 1654 the ſame was done againſt thoſe of the vallies of <hi>Martino,</hi> and <hi>Peroſa.</hi> Theſe <hi>Miſſionary</hi> Fathers beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themſelves among them, more cruelly than <hi>Turks,</hi> or <hi>Barbarians.</hi> But reſolving to root the Proteſtants from among them, and thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to do the work of their Father, the Pope, in the midſt of winter, which is very ſharp in thoſe mountains <hi>viz.</hi> 25 <hi>Jan.</hi> 1655. they procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red an Order, for the Baniſhment of all the Proteſtants, out of the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of <hi>Lucerna, Lucernetta,</hi> St. <hi>Giovanni, La Terre, Bubbiana, Fenite, Compiglione, Bercheraſſio;</hi> and St. <hi>Secondo,</hi> within three days after pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, unleſs they would turn <hi>Roman</hi> Catholiks, and this extended to all in general, none exempted, of what rank, degree, or condition ſoever.</p>
            <p>And thus theſe poor creatures, were forced in compliance to this cruel edict, to fly to ſave their Lives, and conſciences, in the depth of the ſnow, and all the vallies covered with waters, women with child, ſome brought newly to Bed, old women, and decrepit men, leaning on their ſtaves, young children crying and lamenting, dragged over Ice, thorow Rain, Snow, Waters, and a 1000. inconveniences, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, ſo that it would have grieved the heart of a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> to have ſeen them leaving their goods behind them, or ſelling them for little to the Catholicks, who took no pitty of their bitter tears, ſighing, wringing of hands, knocking of breaſts, mourning, complaining, and lamenting, 'twas but as the bleeting of Sheep, or the lowing of Kine in their ears, and they rather rejoyced, than any way commiſerated theſe poor wretches. They were no ſooner out of their houſes, but they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106662:13"/>were pillaged, rifled, and ranſack'd of all they left, pulling down their houſes, cutting down their Trees, making havock, and devaſtation of all things, and turning all into a Wilderneſs.</p>
            <p>This cruel edict was put in execution by <hi>Guſtaldo,</hi> and others; but this is not all, they had a further deſign of extirpating and rooting out all Hereticks as they call theſe poor Proteſtants; it is not enough to have baniſhed theſe few, they could have no redreſs at Court, and all their humble Petitions, and remonſtrances were not heard, for they had more wicked and bloody deſignes, inſtigated by the Miniſters of <hi>Rome,</hi> who had great influence over his <hi>Royall Highneſs,</hi> and <hi>Madam Royal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the 17th. of <hi>April</hi> 1655. whilſt the Proteſtants Deputies were detained at <hi>Turin,</hi> and delayed ſometimes with hope of redreſs, ſome Soldiers of purpoſe fell upon the Proteſtans unexpectedly, who peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably attended the iſſue of their petitions, which begat ſome buſtle, they being but few, the Proteſtants made ſome reſiſtance, whereupon many thouſands got together, under the Marqueſs of <hi>Piadeſſa,</hi> and on the <hi>21th.</hi> of the ſame month, began the moſt horrible Maſſacre among theſe poor Proteſtants, of theſe Vallies, as ever was heard of.</p>
            <p>There was nothing to be ſeen thorow the Proteſtant Vallies, but Churches burning, Towns ſmoaking, Houſes Flaming, men, women, and children maſſacring, nor any thing to be heard, but the confuſed crys of people flying, the peircing groans of ſome dying, and horrid ſcreeks of others tormented: ſo wicked, and barbarous was their uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, that 'tis ſcarce to be expreſſed. In one place they cut off the heads of 150 women got together for ſhelter, and all their childrens brains they daſh'd out againſt the pavements and Rocks, ſome they ſlit in two, and roaſted: And one of the Soldiers afterwards related how he ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitted by eating too much of the fryed brains of a Proteſtant.</p>
            <p>It was afterwards certified from very good hands, of all theſe exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable murthers committed upon theſe poor people, by people of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and credit, and many of them eye-witneſſes. One <hi>Sarah Vignes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they could not make her ſay, <hi>Jeſus, Maria,</hi> they ript up alive, by putting a Sickel into her privy parts, and ſo ſlit up her belly: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had their breaſts, Hands, noſes, and privities cut off, and ſo left for miſerable ſpectacles. Another they ſtab'd often in the ſoles of his feet, then cut off his privities, and fry'd them, and gave their comrades to eat, as a delicate diſh; then they ſear'd his wounds with ſtaming Candles, cut off his ears, and then tore off his nails with burning pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and all this to renounce his Religion, which he ſtill perſiſting in, they tyed one of his Leggs to a mule, and ſo dragg'd him about the ſtreets, till he was almoſt dead, and laſtly binding a cord about his head, they twiſted it with a ſtick, till his eyes and brains burſt forth, caſting his body into the River.</p>
            <p>Another one <hi>Peter Simond</hi> of <hi>Angrogna,</hi> they bound hand and foot,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106662:14"/>and ſlung him down a fearful precipice, but in his fall, by the way, lighting on the ſtump of an old tree, growing in the Rocks, he there hung in a moſt languiſhing condition, for ſeveral days, ere he dy'd, not being able to help himſelf, and the precipice being ſo great, that no other could come at him.</p>
            <p>One of 90. years old they hack'd limbmeal, and then cut off his head: Others had their bellies ript'd up, and their Gutts hung upon the hedges in the high ways. One very old woman had her hands and noſe cut off, and ſo left.</p>
            <p>They ſliced all the fleſh from the bones of another woman, and chopped it like mince-meat: The daughter of <hi>Giovanni Carbonier</hi> of <hi>la Torce,</hi> they took, and putting a long ſtake into her privities, carried her ſo on their ſhoulders, till being weary, they ſtuck the ſtake faſt into the ground, and ſo left her. <hi>Andrea Michalim</hi> ſaw three of his Children torn limb-meal before his face, and the youngeſt being the fourth, its brains daſh'd out againſt the Rocks. Others they tormented by ſlaying off their skins alive, in long ſlices, to make them points: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral drawn at the tayls of their mules thorow the ſtreets, and others following them with brickbats and ſtones, miſerably bruſing them till they dyed.</p>
            <p>The daughter of one <hi>Peter Fontana,</hi> a beautifull Girl, being about ten years old, taken by theſe lecheerous beaſts, becauſe ſhe was not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being forced in an ordinary way, they tore her ſo inhumanly, that they left her almoſt dead, wallowing in her blood.</p>
            <p>The daughter of one <hi>Moſes Long,</hi> about ten years old, they brauched upon a pike, and roaſted her alive, with a fire made upon a broad ſtone.</p>
            <p>One of the Elders of the Church of <hi>Bobio,</hi> they took, and binding his hands and privities together, hang'd him up by them upon a Gate, and ſo left him in exquiſite torments, in that ſhamefull poſture; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others they hang'd up by their privities, and their hands bound behind them.</p>
            <p>One <hi>Roſtagnal of Bobio,</hi> being 80. years old, had his noſe, ears, and other Parts of his body cut off, and ſo left languiſhing in the ſnow till he dyed.</p>
            <p>Four Brothers, and a man, and his wife, all at one time, had their mouths crammed full of gunpowder, and ſo being fired, their heads blown to peeces.</p>
            <p>The Schoolmaſter of <hi>Roras</hi> being ſtript naked, after they had torn off his nails with pincers, and made a 1000. holes in his hands with their daggers, they drag'd him thorow the Borough of <hi>Lucerna,</hi> with a cord, the Souldiers ſtanding on each ſide, hacking and cutting off col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops of his fleſh, as he was hauld along, ſtill crying to him, <hi>will you go to Maſs you dog?</hi> at laſt, they cut off his head, and ſlung him into the River <hi>Pelis.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106662:14"/>
            <p>Another of the ſame place, they took, and put out his eyes, then cut off his privities, and thruſting his yard into his mouth, expoſed him in that poſture to their publique ſcorn ſeveral days together: and after that they flea'd him alive, after a moſt inhumane manner, and then cutting his skin in 4 peeces, hung it in the windows, of 4 of the principal houſes of <hi>Lucerna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They took out the brains of one <hi>Daniel Cardon,</hi> and frying them in a pan, eat them up like Canibals.</p>
            <p>Four old women, being 80. and 90. years old apeece, they burned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live.</p>
            <p>Several they cut to peeces, and gave their fleſh to the dogs.</p>
            <p>In another place having taken 11. men, they heated a great Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, and forced them to ſling one another into it, till they came to the laſt man, which they flung in themſelves.</p>
            <p>Others they ſtab'd with impoyſoned knives, in the legs, and feet, and ſo left them in torment till they dyed. One <hi>Chiairet</hi> was flea'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live and his greaſe taken out of his body. The like was done to ſeveral others. One <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtino</hi> had his noſe, paps, and privities cut off, and then his head cleft in twane. Several Infants were in the ſnow. Several ſtoned to death. One <hi>Gros</hi> the Son of a Miniſter, being taken by them had his fleſh cut off alive, by ſmall gobbets, in the preſence of his wife, and children, which they murther'd before his face. One woman with 7. children, were all barbarously murther'd in their Beds. One <hi>Daniel Rambant</hi> of <hi>Villaro</hi> becauſe he refuſed to ſay, <hi>Jeſus Maria,</hi> or pray to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> they firſt cut off one finger, then another, till they had cut them all off, then his hands, and arms, till fter this manner, they cruelly mangled him to death. Others they ſhut up between two ſtone walls, and miſerably ſtarv'd them to death. No kinds of death, and no kinds of torments, were wanting to theſe poor miſerable peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And it would be an endleſs peece of work, to go about to give a particular account, of all that were put to the ſword, drowned, burnt, ſhot, ſtarv'd, ſmother'd, knock'd on the head, and cut to peeces.</p>
            <p>Theſe horrible doings, cauſed the reſt of the Proteſtants to fly to their Armes, which they termed Rebellion, though it were only to defend their lives, from theſe bloody cut-throats. Thoſe who were ſo good at Maſſacring and murthering, are not ſo good at ſighting, the Proteſtants get the better, and with their Arms in their hands, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves, till by the mediation of the Neighbour Proteſtant Princes, and eſpecially the Engliſh, who alſo contributed above 30000 <hi>l.</hi> to the relief of their diſtreſſes, the breach is made up, and a peace made, but ſo as theſe poor Proteſtants remaining, live under the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of their Popiſh task-maſters, and are forbid all manner of traffic; they rob them of their goods, and Eſtates, often times forcing them to ſell their birth rights, for little or nothing; baniſhing their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, raviſhing their Virgins, reviling and mocking the Matrons,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106662:15"/>beating and abuſing the men, ſo that their vailies are become like dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, in which they are kept as ſlaves, kept in and ſecured, by ſtrong Forts poſſeſſed by the Papiſts. Thus you ſee a brief proſpect of what this monſter of perſecution, this Antichriſtian ſpirit hath committed in theſe places. We will proceed.</p>
            <p>You have beheld many ſad and doleful ſpectacles, and if thou art a Chriſtian,<note place="margin">Poland. Leſnae Exc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidium. <hi>And</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uians <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</hi>
               </note> thy heart muſt bleed, at the relation: we will therefore epitomiſe their bloody cruelties, in <hi>Poland,</hi> for there is no place where they have fixed themſelves with any power, but they have alſo ſet up the ſtandard of perſecution. The Churches of Chriſt in <hi>Poland,</hi> have likewiſe ſufficiently taſted of the Cup, and have drank deep of the dregs thereof, eſpecially whereover the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> thoſe wicked Incendiaries, and Boutfeaus of Religion, had any reſidence, for there is ſcarce any maſſacre, Firing, and devaſtation but they have a hand in it, or it is projected by their ſecret plots and Contrivances. They are ſtill going about like ſo many Lions, ſeeking whom they may devour. Their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are dyed red with the blood of the Saints. They are evermore ſtiring up the common people to fury, Rage, and Combuſtion, againſt all that do profeſs the Goſpell. All the ſame things that we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to be done in other places, are acted alſo in this, we will not uſe tautologies, and repeat the ſame things over again, nor grow tedious. But we cannot but tell you, that many thouſands of the Proteſtants, and profeſſors of the Goſpell, have been deſtroyed in this Kingdome, and eſpecially at <hi>Karnun, Dumbnick, Skocky, Carieuzin,</hi> and <hi>Leſnio,</hi> all deſtroyed and burnt for the cauſe of their Religion. The laſt menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned City being one of the moſt ancient, and moſt flouriſhing in all the Kingdome of <hi>Poland,</hi> wholly ruined, and laid in Aſhes, which was three whole days in Flames, ere it could be conſumed, in which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd many hundred ſouls, beſides an ineſtimable treaſure and wealth, no man reſiſting or oppoſing. Here they pull'd off the noſes of ſome, and put out the eyes of others, cut off the tongues hands and feet, of many; gave quarter to none, but kill'd and deſtroy'd, all that they could any ways come at. They pull'd the dead out of their graves, rifled the Tombs, abuſed their dead bodies, and committed all the outrges could be deviſed by the wicked heart of man, ſcarce to be match'd by <hi>Infidells, Turks,</hi> or <hi>Barbarians.</hi> The <hi>Goths,</hi> and the <hi>Vandals,</hi> could not exceed them.</p>
            <p>In the lower <hi>Poland,</hi> many ſuffer'd, whole families were butcher'd, men, women, young, old, murthered without diſtinction. And in the year 1654. fell a grievious ſlaughter among them, putting to death with exquiſiti Torments all they could lay hands on: One <hi>Samuel Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> the Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Czaertzinon,</hi> they uſed cruelly, firſt put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out his eyes, and ſo leading him about for a miſerable ſpectacle, then pulling off his fingers ends with pincers, then they powred down his mouth molten Lead, and while he was yet half alive, clapt his neck
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106662:15"/>between two folding doors, and ſo violently ſevered his head from his Body. So they ſerved the Miniſter of <hi>Dembnick,</hi> and his Colleague, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having ſeveral ways tormented them, cut their throats with a Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zor, and then while breathing, flung them into a pit, and dung, and filth upon them. They chopt off the head of another young Miniſter, with a Sythe. At <hi>Leſna</hi> they cut off the hands of a pious matron, and three children which ſhe had, they murther'd before her face, cutting off their heads, laying one at each breaſt, and the other by her ſide. Another woman having her hands and feet cut off, and her tongue cut out, they encloſed in a Sack, and ſo left her for two days, in which ſhe lived, making a moſt miſerable lamentation. At <hi>Zich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> they dragg'd many out of their Graves, ſparing not ſo much as the bodys of Noblemen, and brave Commanders, becauſe they were not Catholicks.</p>
            <p>The ſame cruelties,<note place="margin">Lithuania. John de Kyaino. Krainski<hi>'s Relation.</hi>
               </note> the barbarous and bloody <hi>Coſſacks</hi> acted againſt the Proteſtants in <hi>Lithuania,</hi> in the year 1648. ſlaughtering all that were not Catholicks, without diſtinction of Age, or Sex. Here many had their Skins pulled over their ears, whilſt they were alive, others their hands and feet cut off. Some their bowels taken out alive. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had their Shinbones bored thorow. To ſome they powred mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Lead in at the wounds made in their Heads, and Bodies. Some their eyes were pull'd out, and thoſe that were hanged up, and down, in every place were not to be numbred. That was accounted a mercy to be ſhot, or beheaded, and kill'd outright. Their wives, and Daughters were every where raviſhed, their houſes and goods fired, and all their Country, and Churches laid waſte, and thoſe that were left alive, and eſcaped the ſlaughter, were baniſhed; in every place was ſeen nothing but maſſacres, and the blood of ſuffering Chriſtians, ran like ſtreams through the ſtreets of Towns and Citys.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters were chiefly aimed at, and always cruelly tormented, among the reſt one <hi>Adrian Chylnisky</hi> noted for his great piety &amp; learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and reverenc'd for his age, was roaſted alive, by theſe barbarous wretches, having his hands, and leggs tyed together, and that leaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he might feel the more torment. In another place, there were above 40. ſuffered ſeveral ſorts of deaths. Neer <hi>Vilna,</hi> the chiefeſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in <hi>Lithuania,</hi> both Father and Son, Miniſters, called <hi>Smolsky</hi> had their heads ſawed off with a Sickle. Another at <hi>Holowczen</hi> had his fleſh cut off by peeces till he dyed. And Miniſters, and others to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of 1500, were bound to ſtakes on the tops of mountains, in the winter, and ſo ſtarved to death with cold and hunger. All the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral tortures, which theſe poor, and miſerable Souls endured, and the ſeveral deaths they were put to, no Hiſtory can deſcribe.</p>
            <p>Thus you have beheld the rage and flame of perſecution abroad,<note place="margin">The Iſlands of Great <hi>Brittain</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> all <hi>Europe</hi> full of Slaughters, Blood, Maſſacres, and Cruelties, by reaſon of this <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> principle; every land, and Region deſiled, fire and fagot in every place, burning, and conſuming thoſe that diſſent from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106662:16"/>the doctrine of <hi>Rome.</hi> But this perhaps ſeems but a Landskip, things done at a diſtance, you may not be ſo much concerned, as if at home, and before your doors and eyes, perhaps it may not affect you ſo much, as the ſufferings of your own Countrymen. The ſire is but painted, it does not heat and ſcorch you, the ſmoke does not trouble your eyes, and you weep not at theſe Tragedies, and are not ſufficiently affected at theſe perſecutions abroad, and at a diſtance. If it be ſo, there is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to let you know, ſome of the ſad and horrible effects of this mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters rage at home, as well as abroad. Do not deceive your ſelves to think Seas can ſtop him from coming to you, or waters keep you ſafe from this paw of the Beaſt; no, he can ſtretch out his claws over the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Frith; he can reach even from <hi>Italy</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>London;</hi> you ſhall behold the ſame monſter, uſing the ſame cruelties, and ſcratching up the earth to bury the Bodies of his oppoſers. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Religion of <hi>Rome</hi> is eſtabliſh'd in its pride and power, there you ſhall be ſure to ſinde this monſter, ſhe rides upon this terrible beaſt, and with it cruſhes the Sons of the earth, and tramples on the Carcaſes of the ſlain, and wades thorow the blood of Martyrs to her Throne, where ſhe ſits boaſting in her Iniquity, and ruling Nations with a rod of Iron.</p>
            <p>And that you may ſee, the frozen North is not able to affright this Beaſt, but that he has gone beyond the wall of the <hi>Picts,</hi> and eſtabliſh'd its dominion as far as the <hi>Orcades,</hi> I will (ſtill obſerving the method I began, in leaving our own concerns laſt) ſhew you alſo ſome effects of its power and rage in <hi>Scotland;</hi> from thence we will paſs over S. <hi>Georges</hi> Channell into <hi>Ireland;</hi> and laſtly behold the ſufferings and martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the Proteſtants at our own doors, and thoroughout <hi>England,</hi> but with the ſame brevity, as we have done all the reſt.</p>
            <p>In the year then 1527.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scotland.</hi> Hiſt. of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paeric Hamilton</hi> having been in <hi>Germany,</hi> brought home with him into bis own Country, the doctrine of <hi>Luther,</hi> and was the firſt that began to oppoſe the blinde ſuperſtition, and groſſe ignorance of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and no ſooner had he began to open his mouth, but Cardinal <hi>Beven,</hi> Archbiſhop of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> mounts the Beaſt of perſecution, and devours this poor Saint at a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. He ſtrait is condemned to the fire for his errors, (as they call them) and ſuffers at St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> 1527. In the years 1534. ſuffer'd alſo by burning, <hi>David Stratton,</hi> and <hi>Norman Gourlay,</hi> and not long after <hi>Thomas Forret</hi> a <hi>Dean</hi> was burnt by the ſame Cardinal. And in 1538. the Goſpell ſtill increaſing, four more were burnt in one fire. The next year <hi>Jerome Ruſſell,</hi> and <hi>Alexander Kenedy</hi> likewiſe ſuffer'd by the ſame Cardinal, and for the ſame cauſe, 1543. the ſame perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Cardinal Archbiſhop, coming to <hi>Edenborow,</hi> cauſed many to be hanged only for ſuſpition of Hereſie, and one for being only ſuſpected to have eaten of a Gooſe on a Fryday. And a woman with a child ſucking at her Breaſt to be drowned, becauſe ſhe would not pray to the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106662:16"/>Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> He cauſed many to be baniſh'd, and many to be impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd, at St. <hi>Johnſtons;</hi> among the reſt one <hi>John Rogers</hi> a Miniſter whom he cauſed to be murthered in priſon, and his Body to be thrown over the walls. 1546. <hi>George wiſchard</hi> was burnt by Cardinal <hi>Miſle,</hi> another perſecutor of the Saints. This <hi>Wiſchard</hi> was a very learned man, and one who had been brought up a ſtudent in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and had prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied many things concerning his own Country, which was <hi>Scotland,</hi> and which afterwards came to paſs. He ſuffer'd very couragiouſly at St <hi>Andrews:</hi> The ſaid Cardinal and divers other Prelats, looking on, and leaning at the window of the Caſtle, on Velvet Cuſhions. In the year 1563. one <hi>Henry Forreſt</hi> was burnt, having nothing againſt him, but what he had uttered in conſeſſion to a Fryar, they had ſent on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to betray him, having only a ſuſpition of him, and all that he confeſſed, and for which he was burnt, was, that he thought well of the Articles, that <hi>Patric Hamilton</hi> maintained, and for which he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd. 1558. <hi>Walter Mill,</hi> who had been a Prieſt, was burnt. He was the laſt man that ſuffer'd by the Papiſts for Religion in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If that we do not ſinde any marks of this ravenous beaſt, perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Ireland,</hi> before the year 1641. in which that grand execution,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ireland.</hi> Sir <hi>John Temples</hi> Hiſtory of the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </note> and Maſſacre of the Proteſtants broke forth, it is not becauſe they wanted a will, and deſire thereto, or that there were not many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors in that Kingdom, but becauſe they wanted power, and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to execute their malice. For the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the Proteſtants, had been watchfull of all their actions, and carefull in hindring their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, they ſtood upon their guard, and with their Arms in their hands, as if they dwelt among Wolves, or robbers, ſo that it was no eaſy matter to fullfill their deſires, by attempting upon thoſe, whom they ſaw ſo well guarded: but they no ſooner found them ſecure, and that a long and amicable living together, had made the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> Proteſtants fearleſs, and conſident of their amity and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and that the troubles in <hi>England,</hi> gave them a deſired opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but inſtigated by the Prieſts, and Jeſuits, which came over from <hi>Spain, Flanders,</hi> and other parts beyond the Seas, the Nobility, Gentry, and commonalty of the Iriſh Papiſts, conſpire together utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to extirpate, root, and branch, all Proteſtants out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> of what Nation, or condition ſoever. The Prieſts telling the people, that they were Hereticks, and therefore ought not to live among them, or have any commerce with them. That it was no more ſin to kill one of them, then to kill a dog, and that it was a mortal, and unpardonable ſin to releive, ſuccour, or aſſiſt any of them, and a meritorious act to kill, and knock them on the head, and that ſuch who ſhould dye, or be any ways ſlain in the execution, or performance of theſe acts, ſhould go immediately to <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> ſhould be free from the pains of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> ſhould have all their ſins pardoned, and they ſhould dye Martyrs. By theſe means and wicked artifices, they ſo exaſperated the people,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106662:17"/>who believe all things their Prieſts ſay, that as ſoon as the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was given, they ſhewed the horrid effect, in the moſt bloody and barbarous Maſſacre, as ever was committed. Nay thoſe wicked rieſts, many of them gave the Sacrament to diverſe of the Iriſh, upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they ſhould not ſpare, either man, woman, or child, of the Proteſtants, and ſaid that it did them good, to embrew their hands in the blood of Hereticks, and threatned them with excommunication, if they ſhould relieve, harbour, or ſuccour, any in their diſtreſs, and told them, that to take from them their goods, and Eſtates, was no more then to take a bone out of a dogs mouth; and before the Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre began, the people were diſmiſſed from their Maſs, with free li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, to ſpoyl, and take away from the Proteſtants, whatever they could lay hold on, and to kill them, whereever they could meet with them, for that they were worſe then dogs, being devils, and ſuch as were accurſed, and condemned to hell and deteſtation. Theſe were the pious benedictions of theſe Holy Fathers, and Brothers, the Prieſts and Fryers, ſo that it was no wonder, that the raſcally riſh were ſo mercileſs and cruel, believing they merited Heaven thereby, though afterwards ſome of them met with a halter for their pains.</p>
            <p>All things being prepared, by the opiſh Agents, and this Maſſacre long before ſecretly plotred, and cunningly contrived, on the 23d. of <hi>October,</hi> 1641. it broke forth, at once thorow all parts of <hi>Ireland, Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> excepted, where the conſpirators were diſcovered, and prevented: But in all places elſe, the whole Land was in a combuſtion and nothing but blood, murthers, rapes, robberys, and barbarous uſages, of the Proteſtants in every County, Village, Town, and City, that it is not to be expreſſed. As it would be too tedious to give you a full relation of it, and which hath been formerly done by others, ſo we cannot paſs it altogether in ſilence, without remembring ſome of their moſt horrid, and unparralel'd cruelties.</p>
            <p>Multitudes were kill'd by the Sword in cold blood, ſome in their beds, ſome in their houſes, ſome in the fields, in all places whereever they could light on them. At <hi>Liſgol</hi> there were above 150. men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and children, conſumed with fire. At <hi>Moehan</hi> above an 100. knock'd on the head. At <hi>Tullagh</hi> after fair quarter given, they were put to the Sword, and murthered without mercy. At <hi>Liſnaskey,</hi> they hung above an 100. moſt of the Scottiſh Nation: at which place <hi>Mac Guire</hi> made the keeper of the Caſtle, Mr. <hi>Middleton,</hi> to hear Maſs, and to ſwear he would never alter from it, and then immediately cauſed him, his wife, and children, to be hanged. There were a 1000. men, women, and children, drowned at one time, at <hi>Portadown</hi> Bridge, and in ſeveral places of that County 4000. more, driving them into the loughs, and Rivers, pricking them forward (being all ſtark naked) with their skenes and butcherly knives. Many to whom they had given paſſes, to go to ſome place of ſhelter, or to <hi>Dublin,</hi> when they had let
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106662:17"/>them go to ſome convenient place, they ſent Soldiers after them. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Towns they laid waſte and in aſhes, among the reſt <hi>Armagh</hi> and the Cathedral Church there: and in ſome pariſhes two hundred Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies were murthered, and a common butchery, was through the whole County, and in all parts of it, many thouſands periſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed by Sword, Famine, Fire, Water, and all other manner of deaths, that rage and malice could invent. Nay, they would not ſpare the very cattle, horſes, beaſts, ſheep, were all deſtroyed, not to eat, but out of ſpight, leting thouſands lie ſtinking and rotting up and down in the fields and high-ways. In <hi>Colrain</hi> the living could not bury the dead, and the ſlain carcaſes were flung in wide and waſte holes, and packed one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, like herrings. In <hi>Killoman</hi> were 48. Families murther'd. In one houſe 22. Proteſtants burned. In <hi>Kilmore</hi> 200. Families Maſſacred: The villains were ſo wicked, that they would not give them leave to pray, before they dyed. Some they buried alive, and ſome they half buried, others they ſet up into the Earth, and ſo left them to ſtarve. Some they put into deep dungeons to periſh at leaſure; others they mangled, and left languishing in the high ways. Some being grievouſly wounded, they hung upon tenter hooks, ſome thrown into bogs, others hang'd up by the arms whilſt they ſlaſh'd their bodys with their skenes, to know how many cuts, an Engliſhman would endure ere he dyed. Many women great with child were hanged up, others ript up, and their guts pull'd out, and their children thrown to the dogs and ſwine. Some they cut to peeces by gobbets, and collops. Multitudes were drowned in Turf-pits, and thouſands were ſtarved to death, with cold in the bogs, whether they were driven or ſled for ſhelter. Children were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to execute their parents, and parents their children, and brothers and ſiſters one another. The women were as barbarous as the men, and as ready in their bloody executions, nay, they taught their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to kill, and ſhewed them to kill an Engliſhman. Some they boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to death in Cauldrons, and they hang'd one woman near <hi>Caterlaugh</hi> on a tree, and her daughter in the mothers hair; another had his feet burnt off by a ſlow fire; their ſpight and malice reached to the graves, and Tombs, which they opened, and diſpightfully mangled the dead carcaſes, of all they could meet with.</p>
            <p>It is impoſſible to recollect, or expreſs the abominable wickedneſs of their miſchievous inventions, or the horror of their bloody execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, performed with all kinds of circumſtances, that might aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the heighth of their cruelty towards them, and that did expreſs their inveterate malice to our Religion. Alas! who can comprehend the fears, terrors, anguiſh, bitterneſs, and perplexities of the ſouls of theſe ſuffering wretches, their diſpairing paſſions, and conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of minde? or relate truly their deep groans, heavy ſighs, loud ſchreches, ſad lamentations, bitter tears, and horrid trembling, and aſtoniſhment? Their reviling ſpeeches, and wicked boaſts and brags,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106662:18"/>increaſed their miſery. To ſee candles made of the fat and greaſe of thoir friends, and kindred, to burn before them; and to hear them cry, they are almoſt tired with ſlaughtering, and that a young Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy ſhould boaſt, to have ſlain 36. Proteſtants as a meritorious Act; they never diſpatched any without expreſſing great malice and hatred, and uſually with this their ordinary ſarewell, <hi>anim a duel</hi> they ſoul to the devil. They uſed ſeveral blaſphemous ſpeeches againſt God, and the Scriptures. At <hi>Kilkenny</hi> on a Marketday they brought 7 Proteſtants heads, and ſet them in the Market place, one of them being a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, they ſlit from the mouth to the ears, and puting a leaf of a Bible before it, they bid him preach, for his mouth was wide enough. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they took, and riping up his belly took out the end of his guts, and tying it to a poſt, whipped him and prick'd him with their skins round the poſt, drawing forth his guts by that means, that they might ſee how long his puddings were. Some women in Labour, and with their children half born, they flung into the Rivers and bogs, without any pity or regard. Some they burnt to death, with ſeting fire to the ſtraw that the poor wretches had tyed about them, to hide their nakedneſs. Others they worried to death with dogs.</p>
            <p>The number was great of all thoſe that fell under their many cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. About <hi>Dangannon</hi> were 316. Proteſtants ſlain. At <hi>Charlemont</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>00. about <hi>Tyre</hi> was 6. barbarouſly murther'd. At <hi>Laugh</hi> 200. drowned. In another place 300. drowned, and in the Pariſh of <hi>Kallamen</hi> were mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd 1200 Proteſtants. They roaſted one Mr. <hi>Watſon</hi> alive, and cut collops out of his Buttocks. They broke the back bone of a poor youth, and ſo left him in the fields, and ſome days after he was found, having knawn all the graſs round about him, and eaten it for ſuſtenance, not being able to wag from the place: yet they would not kill him out right, but remov'd him to a place of better paſture, and there left him.</p>
            <p>In the County of <hi>Antrim</hi> they murther'd in one morning 954 Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and afterwards in the ſame County about 1200. Near <hi>Liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nearvie</hi> 24 were burnt in one houſe. And that bloody butcher <hi>Philim O Neal,</hi> boaſted he had flain 600 at <hi>Gargauh,</hi> and that he had not left man, woman, nor child at <hi>Munterlough.</hi> And in another place he mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd in their houſes above 200: ſo that many houſes were filled with dead bodies. About 12000 were ſlain in the high-ways, as they fled towards <hi>Downe:</hi> ſome thouſands were drowned, and many ſtarved to death with cold: ſo that in the province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> only, there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 15000. murthered by ſundry kindes of torments and death. A boy not above 14. years of age one night ſlew 15. Proteſtants that were ſet in the ſtocks with a skeen. And another that was but 12. years old, two women and an Engliſh woman; A Papiſt, kill'd 7. men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, her Neighbours, in one morning, forſaking nature, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and all humanity, having imbibed thoſe horrid principles, diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into them, by their Ghoſtly Fathers.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:106662:18"/>
            <p>He that has a minde to be more fully ſatisfied of all their bloudy but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, may reade Sir <hi>John Temples</hi> Book of the <hi>Iriſh Rebellion,</hi> and that they are not falſly or maliciouſly put upon them, they may there ſee the parties names, and the ſeveral witneſſes, who gave in upon oath all that has been here related, ſo that it is ſtill upon record, and among the Rolls of that Kingdom, and will not be forgotten by poſterity. The ſlaughter and butchery was great, the beaſt had here a full feaſt, and he was gorged and glutted with bloud; for according to the ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt account and computation that could be taken, there was murthered and made away in cold bloud, by theſe execrable <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe kill'd in ſight) from the firſt beginning of this horrid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, to the ceſſation of arms, <hi>Sept.</hi> 15. 1643. which was not full two years, above 300000 <hi>Britiſh</hi> Proteſtants, <hi>Engliſh, Welch</hi> and <hi>Scotch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now return home and leave this Land polluted with bloud and Murthers, and let us ſee if our own Countrey had eſcaped from beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a prey to this Monſter:<note place="margin">England.</note> Engliſhmen are naturally of a kinde and loving heart, of a merciful nature and pittiful diſpoſition; they are apt to be touched with the miſeries of others, and they are not in their own natures bloudy, barbarous, nor cruel: But we ſhall anon behold the marks of their rage, we ſhall behold the land flaming with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Martyrs, and the ſtreets running down with bloud, this fair <hi>Iſland</hi> to become an <hi>Acheldama,</hi> a field of skulls and Martyrs bones: We may ſee Tragedies Acted in every place, and the Monſter glutting himſelf with the fryed fleſh of Saints. It is then from the principles of their corrupted Religion, the <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> as well as others obtain this cruelty and fierce nature, and become ſo unrelenting, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, as to cut the throats of their friends, Neighbours, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance. It is this horrid Monſter of perfecution, which this Popiſh Religion rides, and which bears in triumph the pomp and pride of men, and by which <hi>Rome</hi> maintains its power and greatneſs, over as well the Souls as bodies of poor and ignorant wretches, and carries Kings Captive in chains, and makes the great ones ſtoop to its great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and humble themſelves at his feet, and by which the Pope and his conclave have intruded yoaks and fetters, on the hands and necks of Princes, and enſlaved the whole Chriſtian world. This is it that alters the very nature of Engliſhmen, and makes them like <hi>Turks, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels,</hi> and <hi>Barbarians;</hi> The venom of this Monſter being ſuck'd in with the principles of Popery, infects the blood, and envenoms the Soul: Inſtead of being meek and humble, it makes them proud and arrogant; inſtead of obſerving the commands of Chriſt, it performs that of the People, though never ſo contrary: If Chriſt ſays, <hi>hurt no man, pray for your perſecutors, ſubmit to Magiſtrates, and Governours,</hi> the Pope and his Doctrine ſays, kill every man that is not of your Religion, curſe thoſe that diſobey your commands, kill, ſtab, depoſe your King and Governours. This is the Doctrine, theſe the principles and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106662:19"/>of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, and has been ever ſince ſhe was polluted and defiled, and had once beſtrid this bloody Monſter to maintain her pride and greatneſs.</p>
            <p>It was very early,<note place="margin">Engliſh Hiſt. <hi>Fox</hi> Book of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</note> that this bloody beaſt of perſecution began to ſhew his fangs, and his ſharp nails, and armed paws, and it was early that this <hi>Iſland</hi> found thoſe who began to perceive, and to teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the corruptions, and ſuperſtitions of <hi>Rome.</hi> As high as the year 1200. When <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> plainly ſet forth the oppreſſion and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the Pope, and his creatures, and after him <hi>John Groſthead</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> who wrote to the Pope, and admoniſhed him, for which he had like to have ſuffer'd. But the Monſter did but yet ſhew his teeth, and waited for the bloody banquet, he afterwards obtained. But we may finde more early teſtimonies againſt the corruptions of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, ſo that they need not tell us, as they often imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently do, of <hi>Luther,</hi> and the newneſs of our Religion, for in the year 884, <hi>John Patric Erigena</hi> a <hi>Britain,</hi> ordained the firſt Reader at <hi>Oxford,</hi> by King <hi>Alfred,</hi> who was condemned and Martyr'd by the Pope, for wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Book concerning the Sacrament. In the year 960. many Divines wore the marks of this beaſt in their face, being by order from the Pope, branded in their faces with red hot irons, for diſſenting in many things about the Maſs and Purgatory, Monkery, and ſuch like, and for calling <hi>Rome Babylon,</hi> and Cloyſters the Nurſes of <hi>Sodomy;</hi> and 1126. one <hi>Arnold</hi> an Engliſh man, and a preacher, was but chered at <hi>Oxford,</hi> for preaching againſt the pride of the prelates, and the wicked lives of the Prieſts. <hi>Anno</hi> 1160. the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> came hither for ſuccour, and were perſecuted and condemned, burnt, whipt, and ſtigmatized for their Religion, both at <hi>Oxford</hi> and other places.</p>
            <p>Almoſt in every year, God raiſed up many learned and good men, to give their. Teſtimonies againſt the corruption of <hi>Rome,</hi> both by preaching, diſputing, and writing againſt them, as 1170. <hi>Gualo,</hi> and <hi>Gilbert Foliot,</hi> Doctor in Divinity. 1200. <hi>Silveſter Gerald.</hi> 1207. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> a Divino. 1210. <hi>Gualter Maxes,</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Oxford.</hi> 1255. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York.</hi> 1260. <hi>William Stringham,</hi> Doctor of Divinity. 1270. <hi>Roger Bacon,</hi> fellow of <hi>Merton</hi> a Divine, and Mathematitian. 1290. <hi>John Scotus</hi> the great Schoolman. 1320. <hi>John Baranthorp</hi> Doctor. 1326. <hi>John Lyran</hi> a Divine of <hi>Oxford,</hi> 1330. <hi>John Okeham</hi> called <hi>Doctor ſingularis.</hi> 1340. <hi>Thomas Bradwardine.</hi> 1351. <hi>Nicholas Orum.</hi> Doctor of <hi>Oxford.</hi> 1355. <hi>Rich. Filzrulf</hi> Chancellor of <hi>Oxford:</hi> and about the ſame time Doctor <hi>John Wicklif:</hi> and our famour Poet <hi>Jeffery Chaucer.</hi> 1379. <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Wickham,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi> 1382. <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Repington.</hi> 1429. <hi>Alexander Carpenter</hi> of <hi>Oxford.</hi> 1440. <hi>John Felton</hi> of <hi>Magdalen</hi> Colledge. 1460. <hi>John Capgrave</hi> Doctor of Divinity at <hi>Oxford.</hi> 1470. <hi>Henry Parker.</hi> All theſe grave ample teſtimonies, by their publique writings, againſt their many corruptions, and evil Doctrines, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſtitions worſhip of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, with the hazard of their lives,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106662:19"/>Honours, Liberties, Eſtates, and Fortunes. So that many were perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſome burnt under King <hi>Henry</hi> the 2d. 1174. and 1380. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tred Bolton,</hi> and <hi>John Aſhwerly</hi> endured perſecution. 1382. <hi>John Aſhton.</hi> 1390. <hi>Walter Brute,</hi> and <hi>John Pateskul.</hi> 1392. Doctor <hi>Crump</hi> were perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted. 1400. <hi>William Sawtree</hi> a Divine of <hi>Oxford</hi> was Martyr'd. 1401. <hi>William Swinderly</hi> was burnt in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> 1407. <hi>William Thorp</hi> ſuffer'd. 1420. <hi>Lawrence Redman</hi> and ſix others grieviouſly perſecuted. 1417. Lord <hi>Cobham</hi> was burnt in St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s fields. 1421. <hi>John Purvey</hi> Martyr'd. 1428. <hi>William White</hi> burnt: and the ſame year <hi>Richard White.</hi> 1433. <hi>Peter Clark</hi> a Divine of <hi>Oxford,</hi> for maintaining publiquely the Doctrin of <hi>Wickliff</hi> was fain to fly, but was taken beyond the Seas, and his tongue cut out, then hang'd, and afterwards burnt. 1442. <hi>Roger Ovely</hi> was hang'd and quarter'd. 1447. <hi>Humphry Duke</hi> of <hi>Gloſter</hi> was Murthered in priſon by the Popiſh party, for being a favourer of the preachers of the purer Religion. And ſeveral others, that were divers ways perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, for the ſake of Religion, before the riſing up of <hi>Luther:</hi> God having in ages, raiſed up ſome to teſtify to the truth, and to maintain the purity of his Goſpel.</p>
            <p>We have mentioned to you only the Divines, learned and great men, that ſuffered by the cruelty of perſecution, but there were alſo ſundry, and diverſe lay men, that then openly owned the truth, and ſuffered for it, for 1409. <hi>John Badly,</hi> a Taylor was burnt in <hi>Smithfield. William Thorp, John Aſhton, John Purvy,</hi> and others ſuffered for <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifs</hi> Doctrin. And as the number of the faithfull increaſed, who now began to be called <hi>Lollards,</hi> ſo perſecution grew hotter, and the rage and malice of the Papiſts were augmented. 1413. In the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 5th. Sir <hi>Roger Acton, John Brown,</hi> and <hi>John Beverly,</hi> were put to death in t. <hi>Giles</hi>'s fields, and divers others to the number of 36. 1436. <hi>John Claydon,</hi> a <hi>Coriar</hi> of <hi>London</hi> was burnt: and with him <hi>Richard Turning</hi> a <hi>Baker,</hi> 1416, <hi>Benedict <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lleman</hi> was Martyr'd, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others, to a great number impriſon'd. 1422. in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 6th. <hi>William Taylon</hi> a <hi>Wickliffian</hi> was burnt in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> 1422. <hi>Henry Web,</hi> and <hi>John Florence</hi> were cruelly whipt, 1428. and 1431. about 120 men, and women ſuffer'd, many of them burnt. 1428. <hi>William White</hi> was Martyr'd, and at the ſame time two were burnt at <hi>Colcheſter.</hi> 1430. <hi>Richard Hoveden,</hi> a Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> was Martyr'd for the ſame cauſe, near the Tower: and divers more cruelly whipped and handled. 1431. <hi>Thomas Bayly</hi> Miniſter was burnt in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> 1439. <hi>Richard Wiche</hi> a Miniſter burnt at <hi>Tower-hill.</hi> 1433. In the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the 4th. <hi>John Gooſe</hi> was burnt. 1494. In the time of <hi>HJenry</hi> the 7th. one <hi>Joan Boughton,</hi> 80. years old was burnt in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and another in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> 1506. Several were ſtigmatiſed; and many did penance, and <hi>William Tilſworth</hi> was burnt in the Town of <hi>Amerſhant</hi> where they forced his own daughter, to ſet fire to the faggots, that were to burn her Father. And two years after <hi>Thomas Bernard,</hi> and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106662:20"/>
               <hi>James Melton</hi> were burnt in the ſame place, and one <hi>Roberts</hi> at <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham.</hi> 1506. <hi>Thomas Chaſe</hi> after many and cruel uſages and hardſhips in priſon, was there murthered. 1507. One <hi>Thomas Norris</hi> was burnt at <hi>Norwich:</hi> and <hi>Lawrence Guſt</hi> at <hi>Salisbury:</hi> and a woman at <hi>Coipping<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadbury:</hi> with divers other per2ons, in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th.</p>
            <p>In the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. the flame began to encreaſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance ſuffered in every place. 1511. <hi>William Sweeting,</hi> and <hi>John Brewſter,</hi> were burnt in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> The ſame year <hi>William Carder, Robert Harrtſon,</hi> and <hi>Agnes Grebyl</hi> were burnt, they forcing the husband and daughters of the woman, to come in as witheſſes againſt her. Alſo Mr. <hi>Style</hi> with his Book of <hi>Revelations</hi> in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> 25. burnt, and 5. other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons accuſed for reading an Heretical Book, which contained many damnable opinions, being the Evangeliſts in Engliſh. 1514. <hi>Richard Hune</hi> murther'd in the <hi>Lollards</hi> Tower, and afterwards burnt. 1517. <hi>John Brown</hi> was burnt. 1518. <hi>John Stylman</hi> was burnt in <hi>Smithfield:</hi> about the ſame time <hi>Thomas Man</hi> in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> and <hi>Robert Couſin</hi> in <hi>Buckingham</hi> were burnt. 1518. <hi>Chriſtopher Shoemaker</hi> at <hi>Newbery. Richard</hi> and <hi>Robert Bartlet,</hi> and <hi>John Scrivener</hi> burnt: the children of the laſt mentioned, being forced to ſet fire to their Father. And it was moſt uſual to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel children to accuſe their parents, parents their children, Husbands their wives, wives their husbands: boſome friends, and Brothers, and Siſters one another. And many hundreds were forced to abjure againſt their Conſciences, or elſe be burnt.</p>
            <p>But now two things greatly encreaſed the profeſſors of the truth in <hi>England,</hi> which were, the bold owning the Goſpel and the true profeſſion thereof by <hi>Martin Luther</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> and the Art of Print"ing, whereby it was more eaſily promulgated and diſperſed thorow every County, and in all Languages. And now the beaſt began to rage, and lay about him, perſecution and ſlaughter was raiſed every where; thorowout the Kingdome, againſt the <hi>Lutherans;</hi> and 1519. many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtants were apprehended in <hi>Coventry,</hi> impriſon'd in naſty dungeons, and 6. burnt. And two years after in the ſame place <hi>Robert Silkeb.</hi> 1423. <hi>Thomas Harding</hi> was burntat A <hi>Cheſham</hi> in <hi>Bucking ham-ſhire.</hi> 1529. One <hi>Sigal Nicholſon</hi> was hung up by the privy members, for having <hi>Luthers</hi> Books in his houſe, being a Stationer at <hi>Cambridg.</hi> Several were abjured. <hi>William Tracy</hi> Eſq; burnt two years after his death. 1530. <hi>Thomas Hit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> was Martyr'd at <hi>Maidſtone.</hi> 1532. <hi>Richard Bayfield,</hi> a Monk of <hi>Berry</hi> after he had been whipt, and moſt cruelly handled in Priſon, gag'd, beaten, bound, and degraded after a ſhamefull manner, he was burnt with much druelty in <hi>London,</hi> continuing half an hour alive in the flames, for want of fewel, and when his left Arm was burned off, he rubbed that ſide with his right, till it fell alſo in the fire. And about the ſame time <hi>John Tewksbury</hi> was burnt alſo in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> Several impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, and fed with bread made of ſawduſt. Many ſet in the ſtocks, with Iron collars about their necks, and ſeveral racked till they were
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106662:20"/>lamed. 1532. <hi>James Baynham</hi> was alſo burnt in <hi>Smithfield. John Bent</hi> at the <hi>Deviſes:</hi> and one <hi>Trapnel,</hi> at <hi>Broadford</hi> in the County of <hi>Wilts.</hi> Three were hanged in chains, for burning the Image or <hi>Rood</hi> of <hi>Dover-Court. John Frith, Andrew Hewet,</hi> and divers others were burnt <hi>Thomas Bennet, William Tyndal, John Lambert, William Leiton,</hi> and <hi>Collins,</hi> a Lawyer burnt, and <hi>Robert Packington</hi> Murther'd. And one <hi>Peck</hi> burnt at <hi>Ipſwich.</hi> Doctor <hi>Barns,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Garrat</hi> in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> and alſo <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Hieron</hi> in the ſame place; <hi>John Potter</hi> Murther'd in Priſon. <hi>Thomas Bernard,</hi> and <hi>James Morton.</hi> 1544. <hi>Robert Teſtwood, Anthony Parker, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Filmer,</hi> at <hi>Winaſor.</hi> 1541. about 500 in and about <hi>London,</hi> either dyed in Priſon, or fryed in the fire in <hi>Smithfield. Danlip, Dod, Saxie,</hi> and others ſlain. One <hi>Henry</hi> at <hi>Colcheſter, Kerby,</hi> and <hi>Clark</hi> at <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> and <hi>Bury.</hi> And 1546. <hi>Anne Asken</hi> after ſhe had been moſt cruelly rackt, (and that by the Chancellor himſelf, who having a more cruel heart then the Executioner, racked her to the higheſt extremity,) was burnt in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> At the ſame time alſo <hi>Belerrain, Adams,</hi> and <hi>Lacells,</hi> and one <hi>Rogers</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all this was nothing, to the rage and Executions of bloody <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> and wicked <hi>Gardyner,</hi> two notable agents of cruelty and Tiranny, and who ſtoutly ſpurred on the raging beaſt of perſecution, in the days of Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> Then the Proteſtants fell by heaps: then ſuffered <hi>George Hooper, Rogers, Taylor, Bradford, Sanders,</hi> all ſamous then. And 1555. <hi>Thomas Tomkins,</hi> whoſe hands <hi>Bonner</hi> burnt in Priſon with a Torch, to make tryal of his conſtancy, and afterwards cauſed him to be burnt in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> Then <hi>William Hanter</hi> cruelly us'd and burnt. <hi>Hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed,</hi> and <hi>Raily</hi> in <hi>Eſſex. Pigot, Knight,</hi> and <hi>Lawnence,</hi> at ſeveral places in <hi>Eſſex.</hi> Doctor <hi>Ferrar</hi> Biſhop of St. <hi>Davids</hi> burnt there. <hi>Rawlins, White,</hi> at <hi>Cardiff. George Marſh</hi> at <hi>Cheſter. William Elower</hi> at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. John Cardmaker</hi> a Miniſter in <hi>Smithfield:</hi> and with him <hi>John Warn, Sympſon,</hi> and <hi>Ardley,</hi> in <hi>Eſſex. Thomas Hawks,</hi> at <hi>Cogſh ill</hi> in <hi>Eſſex. Walls, Oſmond, Banford, Osborn,</hi> all burnt alſo in <hi>Eſſex. Bland, Shetterden, Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleton, Frankeſh,</hi> all burnt. Alſo <hi>Hall, Wade, Harpole, Joan Beach,</hi> and <hi>Margery Boly,</hi> in <hi>Kent. Carver, Launder, Ireſon, Denby, Newman, Pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham, Hook,</hi> all Martyr'd in ſeveral places. <hi>Coker, Hooper, Lawrence, Collier, Write, Stere,</hi> at <hi>Canterbnry.</hi> The Priſons were now full in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place, and nothing but cruelty, and oppreſſion thorow all the Land. <hi>Robert Samuel,</hi> Miniſter ſuffered Martyrdom at <hi>Norwich. Anne Potten,</hi> and <hi>Joan Trunchfield</hi> at <hi>Ipſwich. William Allen</hi> at <hi>Walſingham. Loe</hi> in <hi>Suffolk. Cob</hi> at <hi>Thetford.</hi> Five more in the <hi>Dioceſs</hi> of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> Two more at <hi>Litchfield. Glover,</hi> and <hi>Bonge,</hi> in the ſame <hi>Dioceſs. Oliver Richardine</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire. Wolſey,</hi> and <hi>Pigot</hi> at <hi>Ely.</hi> The famous <hi>Ridly</hi> and <hi>Latimer</hi> at <hi>Oxford.</hi> Four more at <hi>Canterbury.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Philpot</hi> in <hi>Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1556. ſtill continues their wicked, and bloody rage, the land ſtill is all in a flame, and Blood and cruelty reigneth in every place.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106662:21"/>The bloody perſecutors begin the year, with the martyrdom of 7 per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the firſt month, who were all burnt together in one fire in <hi>Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</hi> and immediately after in <hi>Canterbury</hi> 5 more, men and women. And then followed the ſame year, Doctor <hi>Cranmers</hi> Martyrdom at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> who had been <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> Three more at <hi>Salisbury.</hi> Six more condemned by <hi>Bonner</hi> and burnt; two more at <hi>Rocheſter</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi> Six at <hi>Cholcheſter. John Hullier</hi> Miniſter ſuffer'd at <hi>Ely.</hi> Two at <hi>Bow:</hi> Four more in <hi>Smithfield;</hi> two at <hi>Gloceſter.</hi> Three at <hi>Beckles</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi> Four at <hi>Lewis</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi> And two more preſently after in the ſame place. One at <hi>Leiceſter:</hi> and 11 men and two women, at <hi>Strat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-Bow. Roger Barnard,</hi> at St. <hi>Edmunds Bury.</hi> Two at <hi>Newberry;</hi> three women in the Iſle of <hi>Guernſy,</hi> one of which being great with child, as ſoon as the fire took hold of her, had her belly burſt, and the child ſprung forth alive, being a boy, but was adjudged preſently to be flung into the fire, and burnt, which was accordingly done. Four more burnt at <hi>Greenſtead</hi> in <hi>Suſſex. Thomas Moore</hi> at <hi>Leiceſter. Joan Waiſt</hi> at <hi>Darby. Edward Sharp</hi> at <hi>Briſtow:</hi> Another in the ſame place: Four more in <hi>Suſſex.</hi> Two in <hi>Gloceſterſhire,</hi> and 15 in <hi>Canterbury.</hi> 5 more in one fire in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> Two in S. <hi>Georges</hi> fields in <hi>Southwark</hi> 7 in one fire at <hi>Maidſtone.</hi> 3 men and 4 women more in the ſame <hi>Dioceſſe.</hi> 10 more all burnt together in one fire at <hi>Lewis</hi> in <hi>Suſſex:</hi> being 6 men and 4 wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. One burnt by the Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi> Two at <hi>Lin. Roſe Allen</hi> had her hand burnt with a Candle till the Sinnues crack'd aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. 6 more at <hi>Colcheſter.</hi> 3 more at <hi>Norwich.</hi> Two in <hi>Rocheſter.</hi> Mrs <hi>Lewis</hi> in <hi>Warwickshire.</hi> 4 more at <hi>Iſlington.</hi> Two women at <hi>Colcheſter. John Noys</hi> at <hi>Laxelield</hi> in <hi>Suffolk Cicely Orms</hi> at <hi>Norwich:</hi> ſeveral at <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter. Thomas Spurdame</hi> in <hi>Bury.</hi> 5 more in <hi>Smithfield, Cuthbert Symſon</hi> cruelly rack'd, 3 times in one day, and then burnt with 2 more in <hi>Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field. William Nichols</hi> at <hi>Haverford weſt</hi> in <hi>Wales:</hi> 3 more at <hi>Norwich.</hi> 3 more at <hi>Colcheſter:</hi> 13 more in <hi>Smithfield:</hi> and 6 at <hi>Branford. Thomas Hinſhaw</hi> was whipped by <hi>Bonner</hi> himſelf, with willow rods, and dyed in priſon. <hi>John Wills</hi> alſo whipt by <hi>Bonner,</hi> at his houſe in <hi>Fulham: Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> a Miniſter at <hi>Norwich. Thomas Benbridg</hi> at <hi>Wincheſter.</hi> 4 more at St. <hi>Edmunds Bury.</hi> A man and a woman at <hi>Ipſwich.</hi> 3 more at <hi>Bury.</hi> A woman at <hi>Exeter.</hi> 3 more at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and 5 more at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Queen <hi>Mary</hi> being then ſick, and thoſe were the laſt that were executed for Religion in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have given you a very brief account of thoſe who ſuffer'd in this perſecution, which though but for the ſpace of 5 years, was very ſharp and cruel; we have omitted many, beſides numbers that dyed in priſon, others whipt, beaten, and tormented ſeveral ways, many forced to fly, many to recant againſt their Conſciences, with the like tyranny and oppreſſion every where, and in all places, raving and raging againſt all that profeſſed the Goſpel, and did not fall down before the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Beaſt.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:106662:21"/>
            <p>But now the Death of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and the ſucceſſion of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> put a ſtop to the open rage and perſecution of this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>er. God took pitty of his diſtreſſed people. The pride and arrogancy of <hi>Rome</hi> was taken away, the monſter of Perſecution was baniſh'd the Realm: The power and authority of the <hi>Pope</hi> vaniſh'd, and peace, and Reſt, and Liberty, for all the good people of this Land enſued. The bloody ſangs of the Beaſt, were pull'd out, his Claws pair'd, and the Scorpions ſting in his tail pull'd forth: and all his bloody Inſtruments of <hi>Rome</hi> left to the Judgments and puniſhment of God. But do not think, that this monſter can be quiet, though he be baniſhed the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Dominions of that glorious Queen; and though he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not act in power and ſhew himſelf openly in the ſtreets, and in the market places, for which he grinds his tusks in anger, yet he is reſtleſs; and the agents for this Beaſt are a ſeditious and unquiet generation. They now become miners and Sappers of Kingdoms, and the Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> put on their diſguiſes, and are become dark-lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn Men to act their villanies by ſtealth. They are the Spades and mattocks of <hi>Rome,</hi> they undermine, and work into the Conſciences of thoſe of their Religion, to diſturb the peace and tranquillity of Nations. They are the fire-balls of the Pope, wherewith he puts Nations in a flame at a diſtance. Theſe are his ponyards and daggers, wherewith he murthers Kings, and ſtabs Princes. Theſe are the cunning engines, and framers of maſſacres and private murthers, and by theſe ſort of men, he ſtirs up cunningly the ſanatical party in a Nation, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, the diſſenting, and the Schiſmatical parties in a Kingdom. They are in all ſhapes and diſguiſes: They are rich and full of coyn, to cary on all their deſignes, and to bribe the covetous. They know how to ſatisfie all Scruples, and to pleaſe all humours, they creep into all Courts, and are in all places. They are dilligent in their wicked voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and 'tis their whole ſtudy and employ, how to propagate the greatneſſe and power of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to ſubvert all that oppoſe them: They inculcate into the ears of their people dangerous doctrines, and eſtabliſh in their mindes wicked principles. They tell them, that Princes not profeſſing the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, are abſolutely fallen from their title and authority, that they are no longer Princes but Tyrants and Uſurpers: and that the <hi>Pope</hi> may excommunicate them, and that being ſo excommunicated, their Subjects ought not to obey them, but are abſolved from all tyes of allegiance; that they ought to be thrown out of the ſeat of their Authority; the Scepter ought to be wrung out of their hands, and that 'tis a meritorious act to depoſe or to kill ſuch Princes; that the clergy are exempt from the Jurisdiction of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular princes, and are not bound to their Laws, That the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> hath the full and chief power and command over all, throughout the whole world, even in Civil matters. That the Magiſtrates of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are Heriticks, and therefore not to be accounted Magiſtrates, nor
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106662:22"/>obeyed. And that after the Bull of their holy Father the <hi>Pope</hi> is pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt a Nation, that all that ſhall be then acted, ſhall be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted null and void. That faith is not to be kept with <hi>Hereticks:</hi> and that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath power to abſolve all vows, promiſes, oaths, how ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo ever made or done; with many others of this ſtamp, whereby they alienate the hearts of ſubjects from their Princes, and place all the bonds of Duty on the <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe principles well planted in the Hearts of the people, have cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo many riſings and Rebellions in <hi>England.</hi> How did they perſecute King <hi>John</hi> and at laſt poyſon him in <hi>Swinſtede</hi> Abby, what commotions raiſed <hi>Thomas a Becket,</hi> that proud and ſtubborn Prelate, againſt King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>2d,,</hi> ſo that he made him weary of his life, and to commit murther to be rid of him. How many other Rebellions have they ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up and promoted in this Land? and what Seas of Blood have they ſhed? and how many thouſand Martyrs have they deſtroyed here, and elſewhere? They exceeded the rage and cruelty of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and abominableneſs of the <hi>Barbarian:</hi> they murthered more, and ſhed more blood, then all the 10. perſecutions. There are reckoned in <hi>France</hi> only in the perſecutions of the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> and <hi>Allbingenſes,</hi> to have been ſlaughter'd, a Million of people; and in leſs than 30 years 150000 Chriſtians, to have been made away by the Inquiſition.</p>
            <p>'Tis to bring us again to this paſs, that theſe ſort of men ſtruggle with all diſſiculties, that we may fry with ſire and fagot, and that they may again ſit here as cruel Lords and maſters, that make them ſo induſtrious to animate the blind and ignorant people, to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> having ſent them all packing, with all their trinkets of Superſtition, and eſtabliſht her Reformation and Religion; many penal Laws were induſtriouſly made againſt them, that they might not be able to do hurt and miſchief, which if put in execution, are ſufficient to keep them under, but the indulgency of our Prince hath taken off the ſharp edge of their execution, in hopes to oblige them to a fidelity and compliance, and to live in peace and quiet, but 'tis impoſſible by theſe means to ſubdue them, whilſt their Prieſts have the opportunity to diſtill their dangerous principles into their minds, they think 'tis better to obey their earthly God the Pope, than their Lawfull King and Governour, and to riſe in Rebellion at the command of their Ghoſtly Father, than to live in quiet under an Heretical Prince, as they call all ſuch as ſubmit not their power and Authority to that of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the 5th. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13th. and <hi>Clement</hi> the 8th. all ſent over their Breves and Bulls from <hi>Rome</hi> againſt the Queen, which roar and thunder forth excommunications, Anathema's, and Curſes againſt her and her Subjects. In which they take from her all her Royal titles, Dignities, and Rights to the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring her illegitimate, and an Uſurper, abſolving all her Subjects
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106662:22"/>from their Oaths, Faith, allegiance, and obedience to her,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Foulis</hi> Hiſt. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and Life of Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten all of what condition ſoever, under danger of the wrath of God, not to aſſiſt her, in any wiſe, but to imploy all their power, to bring her to condign puniſhment, promiſing ample reward, to all thoſe who ſhall lay hands on this proſcribed woman, and ſhall puniſh her, and to be paid out of the Treaſury of the Church, and a full pardon of all their ſins who ſhall engage againſt her.</p>
            <p>But when they ſaw theſe would not effect their deſires, and that her ſubjects were too faithfull in <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suintilla</hi> King of <hi>Spain</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by <hi>Childerick</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> murthered 665. <hi>Childerick</hi> the third King of <hi>France</hi> depoſed. <hi>Charls le groſs</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the 7th. <hi>Lewis</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicted.</note> they proceed to ſecret and horrid machinations to take away her Life, from which ſhe was ſtill preſerved by miracalous providence. Their many wicked attempts againſt the Life of this bleſſed Queen, may be fully ſeen, in ſeveral printed Books, largely ſhewing the manner of their proceedings there; my intent only is, to put my Countrymen in minde, of the continual practiſes, againſt both Prince and people, in this Nation and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and whereever they diſſented, or oppoſed the wicked and Tyrannical Power of <hi>Rome.</hi> 'Twas theſe very men, agitated by theſe their divilliſh principles, of King-killing, that violently took away the Lives of the two <hi>Henrys</hi> the 3d. and 4th. of <hi>France,</hi> the one by the hand of <hi>Ravilliac,</hi> the other by that of <hi>James Clement</hi> a <hi>Jacobin,</hi> encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by the Jeſuits, ſet on by the Pope, and the caſe reſolved by the <hi>Prior</hi> of his Covent, <hi>that if he undertook it not for private revenge, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed by the Love of God for Religion, and the good of his Country, he might do it with a ſafe Conſcience; and not only ſo, but he ſhould merit much before God, and without doubt if he ſhould dye in the Act, his Soul ſhould immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately aſcend into the Quiers of the bleſſed.</hi> This was the good councel of this Holy Father, and for which he was afterwards torn to peeces, by 4. horſes, but <hi>Clement</hi> accounted a Martyr, and his murtherous act ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled openly in <hi>France,</hi> both in their Sermons, and printed Books. Theſe are the monſters of men, that would do the like to every Prince, that oppoſes their Luſts. Witneſs their murthering of the Lord <hi>Darnly</hi> the Father of King <hi>James:</hi> of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and of others, of leſſer dignity, and of meaner rank, all that fall under their diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <p>The providence of God, which takes care of Princes, protected this Queen of bleſſed Memory, from their many and wicked Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and bloody machinations. As that in which <hi>Robert Bidulph,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> was engaged 1566. and wherein <hi>Northumberland</hi> ſuffer'd at <hi>York.</hi> This was followed by that of <hi>Leonard Dacres,</hi> and with the like ſucceſs, 1569. Then the invaſion of <hi>Ireland</hi> by <hi>Steukley,</hi> at the great charges of the Pope, happily prevented 1578. Then <hi>James Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moris</hi> 1579. is ſent into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Saunders</hi> with <hi>Legantine</hi> power, and conſecrated banners. And the next year 1580. <hi>San. Joſeph</hi> to them with 700. talian and Spaniſh Souldiers, with the Popes promiſe of 10000000. Crowns to carry on the work of Rebellion. To them joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106662:23"/>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſh confederates, the Earl of <hi>Deſmond</hi> and his brothers, but were all happily defeated.</p>
            <p>Theſe projects failing them, they conſpire the death of the Queen, and make ſeveral attempts to Murther her. Firſt by <hi>Somervil,</hi> and <hi>Hall</hi> a Prieſt, who being condemned was found ſecretly Murther'd, leſt he ſhould betray others, 1583. Then the practiſes of <hi>Mendoza</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh Leiger</hi> here, with <hi>Throgmorton,</hi> and <hi>Parry,</hi> who had Letters of plenary Indulgences, pardon, and remiſſion of all his ſins, ſent him by the Pope, wrote by Cardinal <hi>Como,</hi> and beſides the merit, he ſhould obtain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in Heaven, the Pope promiſes to remain his debtor, for killing the Queen: for which attempt he was exeeuted in <hi>March,</hi> 1585. The ſame year <hi>Savage,</hi> made the ſame vow, to kill the Queen, being inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated thereto by <hi>Gifford,</hi> and <hi>Hodgſon</hi> Prieſts, and 1586. the ſame is taken up by <hi>Babington,</hi> upon the ſame principles, inculcated by <hi>Ballard</hi> a <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> for which they were convicted and executed, and by the Popiſh party eſteemed Martyrs. Then by means of the French Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, they dealt with <hi>Stafford,</hi> and <hi>Moody,</hi> the latter propoſing to lay a bag of gunpowder under the Queens bed chamber, and that way to blow her up, but this alſo was diſcovered.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſecret plots and wicked combinations failing, the Pope ſtirs up his dear Son the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> openly to invade <hi>England,</hi> which he does in the year 1588. the Pope having beſtowed <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> upon him, and which he now ſends to take poſſeſſion of, with that vaſt and as they call it, invincible <hi>Armado,</hi> of 150. Ships, extraordinarily well furniſhed. 20000. Souldiers, 8000. Mariners and Seamen, 2000. Gally ſlaves beſides Gentlemen, and voluntiers in abundance, ſo that there was ſcarce a Family of note in <hi>Spain,</hi> who had not either a Son, Brother, or Coſen in the Fleet. Of Braſs and Iron guns 2050. with Powder, Bullet, Match, Muskets, Pikes, Spears, Swords, and all things proportionable, with Knives, and Daggers, and Skeens, to cut the throats of the Hereticks: and with them ſwarms of thoſe <hi>Locuſts, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puchins, Jeſuits, Mendicants,</hi> and the Officers of their ſacred Order, (as they call it) the Inquiſition. Beſides all theſe lay ready in <hi>Flanders,</hi> 50000. Old Souldiers, and 288. Veſſels ready for their tranſportation, and all the King of <hi>Spains</hi> beſt Soldiers, drawn from all parts, even as far as from <hi>America,</hi> to this expedition, and had coſt the King of <hi>Spain</hi> before they had ſet out 12. Millions of Crowns. But the goodneſs of God, at that time defended <hi>England,</hi> from the gaping jaws of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and diſcomfitted this mighty <hi>Armado,</hi> and all its preparations, and ſent them home full of ſhame, loſs, and confuſion. The greateſt part of this Fleet was loſt and ſcatterd, and about 10000. of their men periſh'd, by the Engliſh, the Dutch, the Seas, Rocks, Sands, and Tempeſts, being utterly broken ſcatter'd and conſounded.</p>
            <p>But yet theſe ſort of people, will not take notice of Gods Judgments, upon their wicked deſigns and enterpriſes, for all this they ſhut their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106662:23"/>and will not ſee that God is againſt them. They no ſooner recover breath, but they ſend over new miſſions, more emiſſeries, diſguiſed in all ſhapes into <hi>England,</hi> with new plots, contrivances and deſigns. <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pez</hi> and his complices, <hi>Cullen, York, Williams, Squire,</hi> and <hi>Hesket,</hi> enter into a Conſpiracy to poyſon the Queen, ſtill uncouraged by the Jeſuits. and the Spaniſh Miniſters of ſtate. 1594. and then 1599. <hi>Tyroen</hi> is ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up to a new Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> having the ſame Indulgences, and pardons ſent him, as uſed to be given by the Popes, to thoſe who were to go to War againſt the Turks: And 1601. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſends to aſſiſt the rebells <hi>John</hi> Dr. <hi>Aquila,</hi> with a great Fleet of Soldiers, who land at <hi>Kingſale</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> But notwithſtanding all theſe wicked, and execrable deſigns, this Heroick Queen having out liv'd 4. Kings, and 8 Popes dyed in peace, and leaves her floriſhing Realms, to her ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One would think now, that the ſucceſſion of a Proteſtant King, to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> thereby uniting into one body that of <hi>Scotland,</hi> with <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and making up one entire and glorious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, ſhould have daſht all their hopes, and that ſo long and well ſetled Reformation in Church, and State, could not be very eaſily broken and confounded, but theſe ſedulous people, like worms cut into ſeveral parts, retain life and ſence, in each divided bit, they are not eaſily to be overthrown, and though they have ſeen ſo many of their helliſh deſigns ſucceed ſo ill, yet they will not give it over, but encourage one another, in their wickedneſs. Two Breeves were brought over from the Pope, whereby they hoped to put by King <hi>James</hi> from the Crown, and had others in their eye of the Nobility of <hi>England,</hi> whom they would have perſwaded with falſe Titles, great promiſes, both of mony and men, to have laid claim to the Crown, ſeeking at the ſame time, to raiſe ſuſpitions and diſſentions among our ſelves, and ſowing diſcord between <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and dealing again with the Nobility and Gentry in <hi>Ireland</hi> to promote new ſtirs, exaſperating alſo the puritans, and ſeparatiſts in <hi>England,</hi> with many other ways and endeavouts, to ruine this Nation, ſo they might bring in Popery and ſet up themſelves. But God continuing to fruſtrate all their deſigns, and King <hi>James</hi> eſtabliſhing the Religion, and ſervice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſo very oppoſite to their principles, and to all their hopes, they now as it were growing deſperate, enter upon the moſt barbarous and helliſh plot and contrivance that ever was hatched in the brains and hearts of men: that which we call the gun-powder Treaſon, and which we yet yearly commemorate, on the 5th. day of <hi>November,</hi> the day, that not only the King, as the head of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,<note place="margin">Anno <hi>2604.</hi>
               </note> ſhould have then deſtroyed, but with him his Queen, all his Royal Iſſue, the Biſhops, Nobility, and all the chief of the Gentry of the whole Kingdom, ſhould have periſhed together at one blow, and have become a Sacrifice to the enraged Luſts of theſe bloody-minded
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106662:24"/>Papiſts. A plot and contrivance that no Age never could parrallel, no Country ever could produce the like, and which was as miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>vented, and detected as it were by the immediate finger of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thuanus. Foulis.</hi> Hiſt. Hiſt. of the Gun-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der plot.</note> who pointed out their treaſonable practiſes, even within their dark vaults and cellars, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen the very train was laid, and fire almoſt put to it. And for this horrid Conſpiracy not only <hi>Catesby, Percy, Faux, Digby, Garnet, Hall, &amp;c.</hi> Prieſts, great contrivers, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters of the buſineſs, and all ſworn to ſecrecy, with horrid Oaths and imprications, and taking the holy Sacrament, and engaging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, one to another thereby, and their Faith by the Holy Trinity, never to ſhrink from the execution of this their helliſh intention, till it was performed. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> having alſo promiſed them Ships, and men, and ten hundred thouſand Crowns to carry on their work, though perhaps he might be ignorant as to the way they had intended, to begin the execution; for I cannot conceive any Royal breaſt, could have admitted the perfect knowledge of ſo wicked, and monſtrous an Act without deteſtation and abhorrancy.</p>
            <p>It is not my deſigne, to give you any Narative or Relation of this horrid Conſpiracy, that has ſufficiently been manifeſted, and the truth aſſerted and made plain, though at firſt (an uſual artifice with them, and learnt of <hi>Nero,</hi> who when he had ſet <hi>Rome</hi> on fire lay'd it on the Chriſtians) they intended to have lay'd the wicked Acts upon the Puritans, and ſince that, they have endeavoured to make the world believe 'twas only a plot of King <hi>James</hi> his Contriving, ſeeking by theſe means, when they could not blow him up with Gun-powder, at leaſt to blaſt his good name, and to make him odious. But three Kingdoms are not ſo eaſily to be deluded, nor our Governours ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridly Impious, to mock God ſo ſolemnly, with annual prayers and thanksgiving, for the deliverance from nothing, from danger of their own making, and to execute and take away the lives of men, for falſe intended crimes; yet theſe are the ſtories theſe ſort of people relate, and buz about, endeavouring to take off the Odium, and ſcandall from themſelves, and to lay it upon their adverſaries.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> is no ſooner gone, but they begin new diſturbances, theſe <hi>Protenſes</hi> now vary their ſhapes, and transform themſelves into Angels of Light, many of the Jeſuits were known to be among the Presbyterians, and there is none of the Sectaries without them, in their conventions: they can whine, and pray with the one, they can rant and thunder with the other, they can cant, and ſpeak nonſence with theſe, they can blaſpeme, and ſpeak loud with thoſe, they can as well ſpeak in the Tub, or at the Table, as in the Pulpit, and in the Desk: they are all things to farther their deſignes. And we are not now to learn, that the indulgence granted them in the time of the late King, inſtead of making them quiet, gave them freſh hopes, of turning all into a flame, and it is ſufficiently manifeſted, that theſe people had no
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106662:24"/>ſmall hand in our late troubles, and in ſubverting a moſt glorious <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> and bringing in an <hi>Anarchy</hi> and confuſion, in puſhing forwards the buſineſs of Religion, till they had brought all to propha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eſs, in turning a flouriſhing and peaceable Kingdom, into a diſmal ſtage of Blood, and Warr; and exaſperating the ſubjects of 3 Kingdoms, till they turn'd Rebells, and by their means brought one of the beſt Kings, that ever reign'd on the Engliſh Throne, to the Scaffold, and to his Martyrdome.</p>
            <p>There are no light proofs of all this that I have mentioned, and we may boldly affirm, that it was theſe ſort of men, that Converted the moſt famous City of <hi>Europe</hi> into aſhes, and were the Incendiaries who gave fire to <hi>London,</hi> confeſſed by <hi>Hubert</hi> the French-man, that was Executed, and others, and it may be more than ſuſpected, it was by the ſame hands that <hi>Southwark</hi> was alſo fired.</p>
            <p>But nothing can quiet theſe ſort of <hi>Beautfous:</hi> what is it they would have? Could they in reaſon expect, or deſire greater Indulgence and favour than hath been ſhown them, by the beſt, and moſt merciful of Kings? have they not been admitted to Honours, to places of Truſt, and profit in this Kingdome? have they not with the reſt, enjoyed a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect tranquillity and happineſs? not in the leaſt moleſted, nor their Conſciences oppreſſed? has not all the fair means that could be inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, been uſed to with theſe people to fidelity and loyalty, and yet ſee it will not do, nothing can convert them from their principles, they muſt reign, that they may perſecute, and will ſtill endeavour, though with the overthrow of a Kingdome, to attain their deſires. It is not the favours of a mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iful Prince can win them: 'tis not the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Governours, and Magiſtrates can perſwade them; 'tis not mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or Indulgence, can invite them from their Treachery, their Plots, and Contrivances.</p>
            <p>They are ſtill the ſame people, and have ſtill the ſame ends; and we are ſtill lyable to all thoſe dangers which their Helliſh plots do threaten us with. Witneſs now this new Plot, no queſtion deeply lay'd in the foundation, with Jeſuitical mortar and daubing, and which we are not yet able to ſee into, and which has been years in contriving; but the ſame God, who hath ſtill waked for <hi>England,</hi> and has hitherto in a great meaſure ſubverted, and confounded all their deſigns, has in ſome meaſure manifeſted, and made known miraculouſly their horrid deſignes, againſt the King and Government, and againſt the ſtate and Religion: and will I hope in a ſhort time, more fully bring to light the depth and fullneſs of their malice, and pernicious deſignes, which no doubt were very bloody and abominable, by the little eſſay which they have given on the Body of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfry,</hi> ſo barbarouſly mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, for his Loyalty to his King, and for his activity in doing his Country Service, and endeavouring to finde out and detect the bottom of this moſt horrid and bloody Couſpiracy, and to bring to condign pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106662:25"/>thoſe who would have turn'd the peaceable Reign of a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Prince into Blood, and ſlaughter, and Confuſion; and who would have chang'd the face of a flouriſhing Nation to Horror and Sadneſs: who would have overthrown our Altars, and our Religion, who would have enſlav'd our Conſciences, or elſe have burnt our Bodies; who would again have ſet up the Monſter of Perſecution, and have made us all ſlaves and miſerable. This is it they would be at, and to this end they ſacrific'd the life of that worthy Gentleman, and would have done as much to the perſon of his Sacred Majeſty, as is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved againſt ſome of thoſe execrable wretches, had not the hand or the Almighty which defends the perſons of Kings and Princes inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as a ſhield, and proved his defence.</p>
            <p>I have thus given you a draught of the bloody Beaſt, but it is but in little, what a horrid ſight would he be, drawn at his full proportion? But look upon him as he is, view him, and behold the ferror of his Looks: his eyes are flames that conſume the Bodies of ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Martyrs: ſee his mouth like Hell gaping for his prey: Blood guſnes out of his open jaws like Rivers; his bloody Tusks are Racks and tormenting Engines, wherewith he grindes the bones of the Saints. His tail is arm'd with the Stings of Scorpions, wherewith he laſhes Kingdomes; from his throat he belches forth Curſes and excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and denounces Judgements and Death upon all that oppoſe him. It is this monſter of perſecution that the ſervants of <hi>Rome</hi> have ſet up in all places, where they have any power and authority; and by this you may beſt judg of their principles and Religion, by theſe evil Fruits you may judge of the Tree, and of what Spirit they are. Their hopes doubtleſs were great, and their confidence mighty, but Heaven has blaſted their deſignes, and overthrown their machinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and redeemed his people from ſlavery; for which we have cauſe to rejoyce, and to bleſs the Lord of Heaven and Earth, and to praiſe him in the Congregation. Let there be no more difference and diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in opinions, but gather your ſelves together as one man, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this armed Beaſt of Perſecution, and let us conclude in the words of the Royal Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.10, 11, 12. <hi>Deſtroy thou the wicked and murtherous Perſecutors, O God, let them fall by their own counſels: Caſt them out in the multitude of their trangreſſions, for they have rebelled againſt thee: But let all thoſe who put their truſt in thee, rejoyce: let them ever ſhout for joy, becauſe thou defendeſt them: let them alſo that love thy Name be joyfull in thee. For thou, O Lord wilt bleſs the righteous, with favour wilt thou compaſs him as with a ſhield,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106662:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
